<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Journal of the Venetian campaigne, A.D. 1687, under the conduct of the Capt. General Morosini, General Coningsmark, [brace] [brace] Providitor Gen. Cornaro, General Venieri, &amp;c. translated from the Italian original, sent from Venice, and printed by order of the most serene republick.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46313</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1107</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39041</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18207321</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18207321</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107108</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46313)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107108)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1125:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Journal of the Venetian campaigne, A.D. 1687, under the conduct of the Capt. General Morosini, General Coningsmark, [brace] [brace] Providitor Gen. Cornaro, General Venieri, &amp;c. translated from the Italian original, sent from Venice, and printed by order of the most serene republick.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 44 p., [1] leaf of plates : map.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.C. and sold by R. Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed, Decemb. 16. 1687, R. L'Estrange."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Venice (Italy) --  History --  Turkish Wars, 17th century --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  History --  1683-1829 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107108:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A JOURNAL OF THE <hi>
                  <hi>Venetian Campaigne,</hi> A. D.</hi> 1687. Under the Conduct of the
<list>
                  <item>Capt. General <hi>Moroſini,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>General <hi>Coningſmark,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Providitor Gen. <hi>Cornaro,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>General <hi>Venieri,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated from the <hi>Italian</hi> Original, ſent from <hi>Venice,</hi> and Printed by Order of the moſt Serene Republick.</p>
            <p>Licenſed, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 16. 1687.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. L'ESTRANGE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>H. C.</hi> and ſold by <hi>R. Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:107108:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107108:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>THE famous <hi>Sabellicus, Bembo,</hi> and others, give this account of the Original of the <hi>Venetian</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth. In the Year of Chriſt, <hi>421.</hi> the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Aqulteia</hi> and <hi>Padua,</hi> through dread of the <hi>Hunns,</hi> and finding their own Cities deſtroy'd, betook themſelves to Flight, and made themſelves Maſters of the Iſlands of the <hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atic Sea;</hi> and retiring firſt to the upper Shoar, now call'd the <hi>Rialto,</hi> there laid the Foundations of <hi>Venice.</hi> The City it ſelf is ſeated in the inmoſt receſs of the <hi>Adriatick Bay,</hi> containing almoſt Sixty Iſlands, at a very ſmall diſtance one from another, divided by narrow Eddies running between, with a ſmall Mount (provided by Provident Nature) defends from the Violence of the Sea. It is ſtor'd with convenient Rivers, which import all thiugs as well for Delight, as for the Neceſſities of Mankind.</p>
            <p>The whole City conſists of three Ranks of People, the <hi>Patrici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> or Gentlemen, the Citizens, and Mechanics. The Supream Power of Government, is in the hands of the <hi>Patricians.</hi> It is divided into ſix Quarters, containing Seventy two Companies of Common People: One and forty Religious Houſes, Seventeen for Monks, and Twenty four for Nuns. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Front that looks toward the Shoar, ſtand two very vast Pillars, the one bearing the <hi>Winged Lion of St. Mark,</hi> and the other the Statue of St. <hi>Theodorus;</hi> and in the Space between, all Malefactors are Executed. The Cathedral of St. <hi>Mark,</hi> is a most Sumptuous and Magnificent Structure, all of Marble. The Streets are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided with ſmall Channels, or Caneales, joyned together with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Bridges, part of Wood, and part of Stone, to the Number of <hi>440.</hi> The Arſenal, is a place every way ſurrounded with strong Walls, wherein Four hundred Workmen are continually em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in preparing Materials for the Building of Galleys, and the Reparation of the Bridges, who are every Week paid their Wages to the value of <hi>2000.</hi> Crowns. In a word, <hi>Venice</hi> is the Queen of all the Cities in the World, and which is more, never Subdu'd to Foraign Subjection. This is She, that has for ſo many Centuries of Years been the Bulwark of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> againſt the Power of the <hi>Turks;</hi> being Marry'd to the Sea every Year, by the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of throwing a Gold Ring into the Neighbouring Ocean upon
<pb facs="tcp:107108:3"/>
               <hi>Aſcenſion-Day.</hi> In a word, ſuch is the ſtrength of her Situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſuch the Conſtitution of her Government, ſuch the ſtrict Obſervance of her Conſtitutions, and ſo exact the Fidelity of her Subjects under an eaſie and gentle <hi>Rule,</hi> that ſhe may well be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the moſt Renowned City in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe.</p>
            <p>If we conſider the Diminution of her Territorys by the loſs of <hi>Candy,</hi> we ſhall find that Loſs in ſome meaſure Repair'd by the Recovery of the <hi>Morea,</hi> to the Extermination (as it may well be hoped) of the <hi>Turks,</hi> from the moſt flouriſhing and faireſt Portion of all <hi>Greece.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Morea,</hi> formerly known by the name of the <hi>Peloponneſus,</hi> is a Peninſula, from North to South, an Hundred and fifty Miles in breadth, that is, from <hi>Corinth</hi> to <hi>Cape Macapan,</hi> and a Hundred ſeventy five from Eaſt to Weſt, and in Circuit Six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Miles, or thereabout. Formerly it was divided into <hi>Achaia, Arcady,</hi> the <hi>Argives,</hi> the Territories of <hi>Corinth, Elis, Laco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Meſſenia,</hi> and <hi>Sicyonia.</hi> Now it is divided into the Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Clarentia,</hi> containing <hi>Achaia</hi> properly ſo called, <hi>Belve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dera,</hi> containing the Territories of the <hi>Meſſenians,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Elis. Saccania</hi> containing the Country of <hi>Argos;</hi> and <hi>Tzaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> containing <hi>Laconia</hi> and <hi>Arcady.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The chief Cities of it were <hi>Argos, Argo; Corinth,</hi> now <hi>Corinto; Corone,</hi> or <hi>Coron; Dyme,</hi> now <hi>Clarentia; Elis,</hi> or <hi>Belvedera; Epidaunes,</hi> or <hi>Malvaſia; Megalopolis,</hi> or <hi>Leontati; Meſſene,</hi> or <hi>Moſſeniga, Modon, Nauplia,</hi> now <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poli di Romania, Patrae,</hi> or <hi>Patraſſe,</hi> and <hi>Militra,</hi> formerly <hi>Lacedemon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Peninſule is divided from the reſt of <hi>Greece</hi> by a narrow Neck of Land, not above Forty Furlongs, or five Miles wide: Which King <hi>Demetrius, Nero, Julius Caeſar, Caligula, Nero,</hi> and ſome other Princes, endeavoured to have Cut through, and ſo to have let in the Sea round about it; but their Labour prov'd in vain, by reaſon of the Rockie ſubſtance of the Earth. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, Succeeding Ages rear'd up a thick Wall in the ſame Place, from Sea to Sea, which <hi>Amurath</hi> the <hi>II.</hi> afterward Levell'd with the Ground, when he Conquer'd and Sack'd the <hi>Peloponneſus.</hi> It was after that Rebuilt in the Year <hi>1453.</hi> by the <hi>Venetians</hi> in fifteen Days, with the Aſſiſtance of <hi>30000.</hi> Men, but then again utterly Ruin'd by the <hi>Turks,</hi> when they made themſelves Maſters of the whole Country.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Patraſſo,</hi> anciently <hi>Patrae,</hi> from <hi>Patreus,</hi> who Peopl'd it, and
<pb facs="tcp:107108:3"/>Surrounded it with Walls. By the <hi>Romans</hi> it was call'd <hi>Auguſta Aroe Patrenſis,</hi> and by reaſon of its commodious Situation for Commerce, by them much frequented and fill'd with Inhabitants; it is ſeated about Seven hundred Paces from the Gulph of <hi>Patraſſo.</hi> In this City <hi>Diana</hi> was formerly Worſhipp'd, under the Name of <hi>Diana Triclariena,</hi> to whom the People made an Annual Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Young Man and a Virgin, the moſt Beautiful they could find to Expiate the Crime of two Perſons, that were Sacrific'd for Marrying in that Temple without the conſent of their Parents. Here St. <hi>Andrew</hi> the Apoſtle ſuffer'd Martyrdom, as alſo <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,</hi> who was one of the Seventy Diſciples and Biſhop of this Town.</p>
            <p>It is Peopl'd at preſent for the moſt part with <hi>Jews,</hi> who make it a place of Trade, not only with the Neighbouring Iſlands, but with the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh.</hi> However the Air is none of the Wholeſomeſt, by reaſon of the High Mountains which overlook it, always cover'd with Snow, and for that the Ground about it is all Marſhie. In the time of the <hi>Deſpotes,</hi> it was a Dutchie; but thoſe Princes not finding themſelves ſtrong enough to keep it, Sold it in the Year, <hi>1408.</hi> to the <hi>Venetians,</hi> from whom it was taken by the <hi>Turks,</hi> in the Year <hi>1463.</hi> In the Year <hi>1533.</hi> it was Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieg'd and Taken by <hi>D'Oria,</hi> but the very next Year the <hi>Turks</hi> Retook it again, and held it till this laſt ſuccesful Conqueſt of the <hi>Venetians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lepanto,</hi> formerly call'd <hi>Naupactus,</hi> is ſeated near the Gulph of <hi>Lepanto,</hi> ſo Famous for the Battle of <hi>Lepanto,</hi> wherein the <hi>Turks</hi> were Overthrown by the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> with a great Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Men, and loſs of Ships: It is an Archiepiſcopal City, built about a Mountain riſing in the form of a Sugar-Loaf, whereon the Fortreſs stands, encompaſſed with four large Walls, ſeparated by Valleys, whereon the Houſes of the Inhabitants stand; the Port is but ſmall, and might eaſily be ſecur'd with a Chain. In the times of Heatheniſm, it had four Temples dedicated to <hi>Venus, Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, Eſculapius,</hi> and <hi>Diana.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the Juriſdiction of the <hi>Turks,</hi> it contain'd ſeven Moſques, two Churches for the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and three Synagogues for the <hi>Jews.</hi> In the Year <hi>1408. Emanuel,</hi> Emperor of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> put it into the hands of the <hi>Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> not able to defend it himſelf. But in the Year <hi>1477.</hi> it was Beſieg'd by the <hi>Turks,</hi> with an Army of <hi>30000.</hi> Men, who after they had Batter'd it for four Months together, were forc'd to raiſe their Siege, and leave it under the <hi>Venetian</hi> Government, till the
<pb facs="tcp:107108:4"/>Year <hi>1498. Bajazet</hi> with an Army of <hi>150000</hi> men, forc'd it to a Surrender. However the Arms of St. <hi>Mark</hi> remain'd, till it was now last Regain'd by General <hi>Moroſini.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſo call'd from <hi>Corinthus,</hi> the Son of <hi>Pelop</hi>'s, was accounted the moſt Noble and Wealthy City of all <hi>Greece;</hi> and by the means of its Situation, it arriv'd to that degree of Splendor and Pride, as to abuſe the Embaſſadors that were ſent by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans;</hi> which the Senate took ſo hainouſly, that they ſent <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius,</hi> with Orders when he had taken the City, to Level it with the Ground, and to put all the Inhabitants to Sale. <hi>Memmius</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Inſtructions, ſet it on Fire; and the mixture of mettals in that diſmal Conflagration, produc'd that ſort of Braſs, call'd <hi>Corinthian Braſs,</hi> much more eſteem'd then Silver or Gold. <hi>Auguſtus</hi> afterwards Rebuilt and Peopl'd it; but it retains nothing of its Priſtin glory, being nothing but a heap of Ruines, ſerving to harbour a ſmall number of People. <hi>Amurath</hi> the <hi>II.</hi> and <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> his Son, made it the Seat of their Barbarous Cruelties, and ſo Ruin'd it, that there are very few Houſes to be ſeen, and thoſe built out of the Ruines of the former Structures. The Fortreſs that both Commanded and Secur'd it, was call'd <hi>Acro-Corinth,</hi> ſeated upon a high and almoſt inacceſſible Rock, furniſh'd with Wells of excellent Spring-Water; and among the reſt, the Fountain <hi>Pirene,</hi> which was Conſecrated to the Muſes, the Water being very clear, and moſt pleaſant to the taſte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miſitra,</hi> was the Ancient <hi>Sparta,</hi> or <hi>Lacedemon,</hi> ſo famous in Ancient Story, and when in its Splendor, two Leagues in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs. This City is divided into four Parts, all diſtinctly ſeparated one from the other. This was the Habitation of <hi>Menelaus,</hi> the Husband of <hi>Helena,</hi> who being Raviſh'd away by <hi>Paris,</hi> occaſion'd the Siege and Deſtruction of <hi>Troy.</hi> Here the Laws of <hi>Lycurgus</hi> took place; Conſtitutions contriv'd with that Wiſdom and Policy, that their Obſervance preſerv'd the Splendor of this City, for the ſpace of <hi>880</hi> Years. It was taken by <hi>Mahomet</hi> the <hi>II.</hi> in the Year <hi>1460.</hi> and <hi>3200.</hi> after its first Foundation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſtel-Nuovo</hi> is the Capital City of the Province of St. <hi>Sobba,</hi> ten days march in Length, and four in Breadth, bounded by <hi>Boſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> and <hi>Dalmatia.</hi> It was built by <hi>Tuardus</hi> King of <hi>Boſſina,</hi> and is ſeated upon the Banks of the Canal of <hi>Cattaro,</hi> three miles from the mouth of it, and juſt oppoſite to the <hi>Levant Sea,</hi> about <hi>800.</hi> Paces in Compaſs. It has two Towers in the Weſt ſide, and one upon the Sea-ſhoar; but the Walls having been often ſhaken by
<pb facs="tcp:107108:4"/>Earthquakes, are neither very ſtrong, nor yet Terraſs'd. The Caſtle of <hi>Salimanega</hi> which joyns to the Town, and is built upon a Rock, is commanded by the Mountain of <hi>Santa Veneranda;</hi> from whence you may likewiſe batter the Caſtle of <hi>Teſtagick,</hi> which is Terraſs'd, and built partly upon a Rock, partly upon a Mount of Earth, and ſerv'd the <hi>Turks</hi> for ae Magazine of Powder.</p>
            <p>The upper Fortreſs that goes by the name of <hi>Gornigrade,</hi> is <hi>650</hi> Paces from the City. Northward; one of the Angles ſtands upon Earth, the other three upon a Rock. The whole Fortreſs is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>250</hi> Paces in Circuit, and might be eaſily ruin'd by a Battery from the Mountain of <hi>Sliebi.</hi> In the Year <hi>1572.</hi> the <hi>Venetians</hi> having loſt it before to <hi>Ariadene Barbaroſſo,</hi> made an Attempt to recover this Place, under the Conduct of General <hi>Venieri,</hi> but they met with ſo many Obſtacles, and ſuch conſiderable Oppoſition, that they were forc'd to give over the Enterprize, which they never af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ventur'd any more till this preſent Year, under the more ſuccesful Conduct of General <hi>Cornaro.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The onſuing Journal is a Proſpect of the laſt Summer's Conqueſts under the ſuccesful Banners of the moſt Serene Republick of <hi>Venice.</hi> The particulars of which are from day to day ſet down, as it may be ſuppos'd, by the ſtile of the Original, which is in <hi>Italian,</hi> by ſome great Officers, that were Eyewitneſſes of the Succeſs in both Places, and of no ſmall Credit for the truth of the Relation, as being Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd and Licens'd by <hi>Public Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Negropont,</hi> which it is thought will be the firſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize of the next Campaigne, if it be not already taken accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Report, and the general Expectations, it was anciently call'd <hi>Abantis,</hi> afterwards <hi>Euboea,</hi> from the name of a Matron of Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine Courage that govern'd it. This Iſland may well be ſaid to be the Queen of all the Iſlands in the <hi>Archipelago,</hi> as being in length <hi>130</hi> miles, in breadth <hi>30,</hi> and in Circuit <hi>300.</hi> It lies ſtretch'd all along to the North upon the Coaſt of <hi>Achaia,</hi> from whence it is divided by a narrow Frith, not above <hi>50</hi> Foot over; the chief City is <hi>Chalcis,</hi> now <hi>Negropont,</hi> joyn'd to the Continent by a Draw-bridg. In ſo much that ſome Geographers believe, it was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly a part of the Continent it ſelf, and only ſeparated from it by ſome Earthquake, to which the Iſland is ſubject ſometimes. It was formerly ſubject to the <hi>Venetians,</hi> to whom it was aſſign'd by <hi>Raba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Carcerius,</hi> who was Duke of it; but in the Year <hi>1470.</hi> it was ſubdu'd by <hi>Mahomet</hi> the <hi>II.</hi> with a great ſlaughter of the Chriſtians. It has a very ſtrong Caſtle with four Towers, and a well ſtor'd Arſenal.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:107108:5"/>
            <p>And thus we ſee the haughty Turk run down on every ſide, chas'd out of <hi>Hungary,</hi> expell'd the <hi>Morea,</hi> loſing Ground in <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia;</hi> and in a word, the Ottoman Empire, according to all human Reaſon, haſtning to its period. For there is a Spirit of Conduct, Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity and Gallantry, which ranges about the World, and fixes ſometimes here, ſometimes there, as Deſtiny deſigns to turn the ſcales of Succeſs. And this is the reaſon that decaying Empires Languiſh under ſloathful and effeminate Princes. A Critical Seaſon which the Prudence and Vigilance of Inferior Dominion always lay hold of, to wreſt from the feeble hands of Potentates ſubjugated to their pleaſures, the wrongful Conqueſts of their Anceſtors. As if the Spirit and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor of their Fore-fathers were departed from them to their Enemies. Such a conjuncture as this, now luckily fell out at <hi>Venice,</hi> which was never better ſtor'd then now, with Perſonages not only Illuſtrious for the antiquity of their Deſcent, then for their own perſonal Vertues.</p>
            <p>For of the Name and Family of the <hi>Moroſini</hi> we find in Hiſtory, no leſs then Three who were Dukes of <hi>Venice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt was <hi>Dominico Moroſini,</hi> the <hi>37th.</hi> Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> who clear'd the Gulph of the Corſairs of <hi>Ancona,</hi> among whom <hi>Guiſcard,</hi> who was the chief, was taken and hanged: He recover'd <hi>Pola,</hi> and <hi>Parenzo,</hi> revolted from the Signorie in <hi>Iſtria.</hi> He ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Venice</hi> with Beautiful Structures, and began the Tower of St. <hi>Mark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next to him was <hi>Marino Moroſini,</hi> the <hi>44th.</hi> Duke of <hi>Venice;</hi> in whoſe time a Colony of Nobility was ſent into <hi>Candy,</hi> who Built <hi>Candy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third was <hi>Michele Moroſini,</hi> the <hi>61ſt.</hi> Duke of <hi>Venice;</hi> a Perſon of great Learning and Wiſdom; who tho' he lived but a ſhort while, Enacted ſeveral good Laws for the benefit of the Republic.</p>
            <p>The Family of the <hi>Cornari</hi> is likewiſe very Ancient, and reckon'd into their Number. <hi>Marco Cornari,</hi> who reduced the Rebellious <hi>Candiots</hi> to their Obedience to the Common Wealth, in the time of <hi>Urban</hi> the <hi>5th.</hi> Of the Family of <hi>Venieri,</hi> was <hi>Franceſco Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieri, 81ſt.</hi> Duke of <hi>Venice;</hi> who, tho' the <hi>Turk</hi> at the ſame time, made War upon <hi>Puglia,</hi> and the King of <hi>France</hi> in <hi>Florence,</hi> yet entertained the King of <hi>Poland</hi> in <hi>Venice.</hi> And <hi>Sebaſtian Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieri,</hi> the <hi>86th.</hi> Duke of <hi>Venice;</hi> who was choſen with that unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous conſent, that even ſeveral of the <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves, came to kiſs his Feet.</p>
            <p>To Speak more of their Living Deſcendants is a labour beyond the task of theſe few Sheets, which only gives a rough draught of their Great Atchievements, for publick and preſent Satisfaction; leaving the reſt for Histories more Polite and Copious, to render Glorious to Poſterity.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="map">
            <pb facs="tcp:107108:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107108:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of Greece</figDesc>
                  <p>MOREA olim PELOPONESUS</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Iohn Seller.</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="journal">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107108:6"/>
            <head>A JOURNAL OF THE FAMOUS <hi>Venetian Campaigne.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>From the Venetian Fleet in the Seas of</hi> Lepanto <hi>and</hi> Patraſſo, July 25. 1687.</head>
               <p>AFTER ſome little Heats and Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which redounded much to the Honor of his Excellency, my Lord Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, tho' they put ſome ſtop to this preſent Campaign, this Morning with loud Peals of great Guns aboard the whole Fleet, and with moſt Devout Thankſgivings to the Supreme God of Victory, was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemniz'd the appearance of this day ſo much wiſh'd for, which reſtoring Univerſal Prattick to our Veſſels, and ſafeguard to our Seas, has brought us that Joy and Conſolation, which it is not poſſible for any Perſon to comprehend, that does not fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Sentiments of Chriſtianity in his Heart. After which,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107108:7"/>his Excellency made it his Buſineſs. After which, his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency betook himſelf, according to the Dictates of his own Religious Zeal, to return to the God of Mercy, the moſt Devout Remonſtrances of Humiliation, for ſo mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous a Bleſſing. So that upon <hi>Sunday,</hi> the 20th. of this Inſtant Month, being attended by all the Chief Commanders at Sea, and by all the young Patritian Nobility, under a moſt pompous Pavillion he caus'd <hi>Te Deum</hi> to be Sung; and the whole Fleet at the ſame time to acknowledge the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Favours of Heaven, to the Confuſion of our Infidel Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Thus after their Excellencies had heard the Holy Maſs, and received the moſt Holy Sacrament, they retired every one to their particular Commands.</p>
               <p>This neceſſary Chriſtian Duty, being thus ended, and a Reſolution being taken to carry on the Invaſions towards the Caſtle of <hi>Lepanto</hi> and <hi>Patraſſo</hi> to compleat the entire Poſſeſſion of the <hi>Morea,</hi> his Excellency fail'd not in the firſt place to furniſh himſelf with all ſorts of neceſſary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion and Ammunition. He reduc'd the Foot that was to land to about Nine thouſand Foot, all ſound Men, in ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Bodies according to their Nations, under Officers of Valor and Conduct. With theſe he joyn'd a ſtrong Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Thirteen hundred Horſe, and had not ſickneſs very much afflicted the Soldiery, their number would have been much greater.</p>
               <p>Having Embark'd all his Forces, he weigh'd and ſet ſail from <hi>Glimeno,</hi> the 20th of <hi>July</hi> in the Evening, with twenty ſix Gallies, fourteen Galeots, ſix Galeaſſes, Veſſels with ſquare Sails, what with Ships, Fly-boats, Pinks, Brigantines, and Tenders, to the number of Eighty Seven. Which Body was under the Command of Captain <hi>Zaguri.</hi> The Lighter Veſſels, by the help of their Oars, made a ſhift to leave the Greater Veſſels behind, tho' they put forth to Sea many hours after the others had ſet Sail.</p>
               <p n="21">21ſt. Next Morning the Fleet arriv'd within ſight of the Caſtles, and <hi>Patraſſo,</hi> having had a fair Wind, and no leſs proſper'd by the Gales of a Celeſtial Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
               <p>Coming neer the Shore, they diſcover'd the Enemies Tents pitch'd in great numbers upon a Hill, which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looks
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107108:7"/>the Fortreſs; and another great Encampment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſame Fortreſs, and the Caſtle of the <hi>Morea,</hi> ſeated alſo in a very advantageous place. Now to obtain ſome underſtanding of the Enemies deſign, our Ships coaſted along the Shore within Musket ſhot, at what time we could diſcern the Enemy running buſily to and fro, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the protection of a Breaſt-work by them erected above a Mile a this and that ſide <hi>Patraſs,</hi> making a ſhew of a great number of Enſigns, and of much Courage and Reſolution.</p>
               <p>But where the Breaſt-work ended, there they gave over appearing; Which being obſerv'd by his Excellency; after he had amus'd 'em for ſome time longer with his Gallies, he paſt on to the Shore of <hi>Rumelia,</hi> which he ſaw likewiſe very ſtrongly Guarded with Soldiers, and ſuch another Breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work, and near to the Caſtle was diſcover'd another great Encampment.</p>
               <p>General <hi>Coningſmark</hi> had embark'd himſelf aboard the General's Gally, which was therefore ſo deſired by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, that he might have the more opportunity to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with him about their manner of Landing.</p>
               <p>That, it was foreſeen, would be difficult if the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> were reſolv'd to hinder them; becauſe they might do it ſafely under the protection of their Works. Being therefore ſo much as they were a head of the reſt of the Fleet, they reſolv'd to effect it, in the place before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, where the Breaſt-work ended upon the Right ſide of <hi>Patraſs,</hi> becauſe they could command it with the Prows of their Gallies.</p>
               <p n="22">22d. The next Morning therefore the whole Fleet made an attempt to Land, and firſt the Galeots and Gallies them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves being come to the place firſt pitch'd upon, the Foreigners firſt ſet foot aſhore, who were afterwards fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by all the reſt of the Militia.</p>
               <p>The Turks did not appear to oppoſe them, for that the Riſing Ground being paſs'd, the other part being all Marſhie, they thought it not worth their while to make themſelves maſters of it, not knowing where to retire, ſhould any diſaſter befal them. Therefore Marching in ſight of our Veſſels, they went with a Body of about Three hundred Horſe to attack the Right Wing where were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107108:8"/>thoſe of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> and the Foreigners; who giving them the Liberty to approach, ply'd them ſo well with their Musket ſhot, that the Turks were forced to retire, who being purſu'd by the Foreigners left many of their People dead upon the ſpot, whoſe Heads became a prey to our own Men.</p>
               <p>By this Time the People in the Galeaſſes diſembark'd, and the Ships, and flat bottom'd Veſſels being arriv'd, all the reſt of the Horſe and Foot landed, Three Miles from the Fortreſs; which could not happen ſooner, by reaſon the Winds happen'd ſomething contrary. The Turks ſhew'd themſelves in good Order upon the Curtins under the Fortreſs, and were intrench'd upon the Shore after that manner, that they took up two Miles in Front, with a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery of two pieces of Cannon.</p>
               <p>In the Night, by the favour of the Darkneſs, the moſt Excellent <hi>Sanudo,</hi> with a Squadron of Eight ſlender Gallies, paſs'd within the Caſtles, on purpoſe to deſtroy the Barks, to the end the Turks might be depriv'd of the Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of tranſporting their Soldiers out of <hi>Grecia</hi> into <hi>Morea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 23d. the Galeaſſes, and one Pinnace got within Musket ſhot of the Face of the Battery, and in leſs than Three Hours with their prow-Cannons beat it down, and in many places ruin'd their Trenches, and with another Pinnace that ſhot Stones, drave the Turks quite from their poſt.</p>
               <p>The 24th. this Morning which was St. <hi>Chriſtins</hi> day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning their March again by Break of Day, in regard they had a long way to go, they March'd but ſlowly, and keeping an exact Order, at what time General <hi>Coningſmark</hi> ſhew'd his great Knowledge in Military Diſcipline. The Enemy abandoning their Breaſt-work upon the Coaſt, and leaving their Tents, began their Approaches nearer and nearer to our Army, making a ſhew of great Reſolution, but ſoon after turn'd their backs, as if they intended to flee. But the more uncertain their Motions were, ſo much the leſs did we alter our March, yet with an Ardent deſire, however, to come to handy ſtrokes.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:107108:8"/>
               <p>At length, after eighteen hours thus ſpent, the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians approached, and began to Skirmiſh with a Batalian of the <hi>Oltramarine's,</hi> Commanded by Colonel <hi>Ceclina;</hi> at what time our Forces embodying, and the Enemy approaching with all their Forces, the Sign of Battel was given, and the Chriſtian Army prepar'd themſelſes for the ſo long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienc'd Tryal of their Valour.</p>
               <p>The Turks fir'd very thick with their Muskets upon the <hi>Oltramarines</hi> which were upon the Right Wing, and with their Swords in their hands, made a bold Attaque upon their Rear.</p>
               <p>But then the Oltramarines being bravely flank'd by the Friſian Horſe of the Left Wing, ply'd their Small-ſhot ſo nimbly, that the Enemy ſlacken'd their Fury, and were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puls'd with great loſs.</p>
               <p>Quitting therefore this Attaque, they made another Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault upon the Brunſwickers in Flank, where intending to have broken in with their Swords in their hands, they met with ſuch a ſolid and vigorous reſiſtance, that being well mortify'd with the well order'd Volleys of the Muskets, and ſeeing many of their Men fall dead upon the place, after a cloſe Fight of four hours, maintain'd by our Men, who upon all occaſions were ſtill ſuccour'd by the Sclavonians and the Cavalry, they betook themſelves to an ignominious flight, being valiantly purſu'd by the Oltramarines, and by the Marqueſs <hi>Corbon,</hi> with his Cavalry. However, General <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningſmark</hi> would not ſuffer ours to purſue the Enemy very far, for fear of falling into any Embuſcado, and becauſe he would not that the Army ſhould break their Order. So that the Turks making haſte to their Tents, pull'd up the greateſt part, at what time they in the Piazza of <hi>Patraſs</hi> ſetting fire to a Magazine of Amunition, joyn'd with the reſt, and leaving in a moment all that compaſs of Ground in our Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, they all diſappear'd. In this Fight, ſingular was the Conrage and Experienc'd Conduct of General <hi>Coningſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark;</hi> and the valorous Arm of the Prince of <hi>Turrena</hi> did great Execution, who being joyned with the Marqueſs <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon,</hi> lead the Horſe: Nor did the Prince of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> leſs generouſly behave himſelf, who with his Troops was ſtill in the hotteſt of the Action. The Death of Colonel <hi>Ceclina,</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:107108:9"/>ſhot in the Breaſt with a Musket-Bullet, is univerfally la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented; who being by Nation an Oltramarine, tho' he had loſt his Chief Commander, underſtood ſo well with ſo much vigor, to humble the furious Pride of the Muſelmen. Of whom there were Five hundred ſlain upon the place, and 'tis believ'd a great many more were kill'd, in regard of the great number of Tents that were left for want of Owners.</p>
               <p>We took five Pieces of Artilery, beſides two Pieces of Cannon, which were found planted upon the ſhore within their Trenches, when at the beginning of the Fight the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral order'd the Volunteers to land, on purpoſe to divert the Enemy. On the other Side we had little loſs, in regard we kept the Enemy at a diſtance with our Muskets. It added alſo to their greater fear, for that the General in the heat of the Fight, had cauſed a great number of the Seamen to land, who poſſeſſing themſelves of the Trench aforeſaid, found therein the two fore-mentioned Braſs Pieces, and two others at a little diſtance from thence, which form'd the Battery already ſpoken of; beſides which, the Enemy left behind them ſix Field-Pieces which they loſt in the Conflict. Great was the number of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Colours, which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians brought away as Trophies of their Valor, and that which added to the Glory of their Triumph, was, their taking of three Enſigns with Tayles, beſides a very rich Standard guilded; with which the Fringe and Blazon were evident Signs of the Baſha-Generalſhip; of which the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſquier is depriv'd. His Flight, together with that of the Army, was immediately followed by the Flight of their other Party at <hi>Rumelia,</hi> and the abandoning their Tents. And the Night after, his Excellency underſtanding that the Turks had left the Caſtle of the <hi>Morea,</hi> he turn'd the Prows of his Galleys, and he no ſooner came in ſight of the place, but he ſaw ſome part of the Wall toward the Sea, on <hi>Greece</hi> ſide, blown up by Gun-Powder, and the Caſtle left under the Dominion of the Venetians, with forty Pieces of Cannon.</p>
               <p>The General for all this, would not ſuffer his wonted heat, for the Good of his Country and Chriſtendem, to cool, but held on his Voyage for <hi>Lepanto,</hi> to make the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of his good Fortune during this Conſternation of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107108:9"/>Turk: And indeed the Favour of Heaven proſper'd his zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Deſigns, for the Barbarians being ſtill more and more ſeiz'd with <hi>Panick</hi>-Terror, could not endure the ſight of our Veſſels; ſo that ſeeking their ſafety in other places, they retreated, and left to the Victorious Venetians the Piazza itſelf. And thus, to the great wonder of every one, this moſt Signal Victory was obtained through the Favor of the God of Hoſts, with the moſt Glorious Conqueſt of four Fortreſſes in the turning round of one Sun: By which the Public gain'd One hundred and ſixty Pieces of Cannon almoſt all Braſs, beſides a great quantity of Proviſions and Warlike Amunition, together with fourteen Pyrate Barks. So that the moſt Serene Republic now Commands a moſt Delicious, Fertile and Spacious Gulph, a Spacious and Rich Country, to the incredible Contempt and Loſs of the Perſecutors of the Holy Religion and the Chriſtian Faith. <hi>Carlo Piſani,</hi> Captain of the condemn'd Perſons, is alſo deſigned by His Excellency, to take all the Turkiſh Veſſels which he can find in the vaſt Gulph of <hi>Lepanto.</hi> So that after ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and timely Proviſions, we have no reaſon but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ourſelves from the Aſſiſtance of God, for the future, Progreſſes of moſt Remarkable Conſequence for the Honor of the Chriſtian Armies, and the greater advantage of our Invincible Republic.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:107108:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>From the Fleet, in the Bay of</hi> Corinth, Auguſt 17. 1687.</head>
               <p>SO glorious was the Fame of the Valour of the Venetian Armies upon the Overthrow given to the Seraſquier in the late Battel, in the Campains of <hi>Patraſs,</hi> and by the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Patraſs, Lepanto,</hi> and two Caſtles beſides, that the Turks, now taught by the fortunate Succeſs of the Chriſtians, are ſufficiently convinc'd, that Fortune, which for ſo long time has favour'd the Ottoman Armies, to the great Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Chriſtians, has now forſak'n their Side. After theſe glorious Acquiſts, we underſtand, that <hi>Kamor,</hi> Baſha of <hi>Avaruti,</hi> and <hi>Gavar,</hi> Baſha of <hi>Vallona,</hi> both fell under the Valor of the Venetian Victors, being the Perſons who were order'd to guard the Shore of the Continent from this Place to the <hi>Preveſa;</hi> and that of an Hundred and twenty Colours which they had, to every one of which belong'd fifty Men, that only three remain'd ſafe, the reſt were all deſtroy'd.</p>
               <p>They reck'n loſt of the Ottoman Side, about a thouſand ſlain outright, and above as many more wounded, which dy'd in the haſty flight which the Seraſquier made to <hi>Corinth.</hi> For the greater Proof of which, there are many Carcaſſes to be ſeen upon the Road. Beſides a great many which are alſo found in the Country Houſes by our Adventurers, who range the Country to make Slaves of both Sexes, who averr that the Enemy were about Twelve thouſand, being recruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but a little before with Three thouſand Soldiers from <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gropont. Muſtapha</hi> Baſha, who guarded part of <hi>Rumelia,</hi> that is to ſay, the Caſtle and City of <hi>Lepanto,</hi> fled with equal Cowardice, without being purſu'd, and abandoning all, was followed by a few of his own Men, the reſt, to the number of Eight thouſand, taking the Hill-way, while he with hardly Fifteen hundred, march'd toward <hi>Salona:</hi> But that he had not march'd far before he was met by <hi>Iſmael Baſha,</hi> who brought along with him about a thouſand Soldiers from <hi>Salonich,</hi> who then turn'd back alſo, and ſtopp'd two days
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107108:10"/>March from <hi>Salona,</hi> giving out a Report, that the Reaſon of his Flight was upon a Rumor of the Death of the Seraſquier, which happen'd ſoon after the Fight, but underſtanding af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards that he was at <hi>Corinth,</hi> he departed alſo from thence, without any hopes of ever being reconcil'd to him again, for fear of proving the fatal Effects of his Anger.</p>
               <p>How great the fear of the Seraſquier was, may be eaſily conjectur'd, by his cauſing part of the Houſes of the Fortreſs to be burnt, ſo ſoon as he came to <hi>Corinth:</hi> Which Fortreſs ſtands upon the top of an Hill, three Miles and more diſtant from the Sea. He alſo burnt a good part of the City, to hinder the Chriſtians from taking Poſſeſſion of it; command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo all the Families of the Turks to depart the <hi>Morea,</hi> and haſt'ning the flight of thoſe from the places abandon'd; and to facilitate their Motion, leaving the Remainder of his Baggage and his Army at <hi>Thebes.</hi> He attributed it very much to his good fortune, that he was not purſu'd by us, as he thought he ſhould have been: which enabled him to ſave the Remainder that were left him, and thoſe that were ſpread through the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>The foreſaid Places were provided with Governors; in <hi>Patraſſo,</hi> the Signior <hi>Gerolamo Priuli,</hi> under the Title of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veditor Extraordinary; Signor <hi>Pietro Grioni</hi> is made Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable; <hi>Tadio Gradenigo</hi> was made Proveditor Extraordinary of <hi>Lepanto,</hi> and the Marqueſs of <hi>Meliluppi</hi> Conſtable of the Caſtle: In the Caſtle of the <hi>Morea, Marco Barberigo</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for Proveditor, and for Governor of the Caſtle <hi>Gero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo Tiepolo:</hi> In the Caſtle of <hi>Rumelia</hi> was deſign'd for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veditor Ordinary <hi>Aloiſio Sagredo,</hi> and becauſe the Caſtle of <hi>Torneſe</hi> is ſince ſurrender'd, <hi>Zorzy Toſcarini</hi> was ſent thither to Command it. At the ſame time, the Places were all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively provided of Governors, Chaplains, Phyſitians, Chyrurgeons, Hoſpitals, Medicines, and all neceſſary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions for War and Food. There are many Families of the <hi>Gaſtuni,</hi> and of their Ample Territory, which contains an hundred Towns, who deſire to be admitted into the holy Faith. To which purpoſe there is intended a Solemn Office of Baptiſm, and to perform the Solemnity with peals of Cannon, and with all other Demonſtrations, which may ſerve the more to confound the Ottoman Sect. For this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107108:11"/>Conqueſt, by which was gain'd the Poſſeſſion of all the <hi>the Morea,</hi> all due Thankſgivings were rendered to the God of Victory, with peals of Cannon from the whole Fleet, and in the foreſaid places <hi>Te Deum</hi> was ſung with a general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Afterwards the whole Fleet ſet Sail for the Coaſts of <hi>Corinth,</hi> whither a ſmall Squadran had been ſent before to ſecure the Poſition of ſome places; for becauſe this Gulph is uſually very tempeſtuous, it did not fail to ſhew its fury at this time, there being no Port for an hundred Miles toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the <hi>Morea</hi> Side; and on the other Side, only a ſmall Bay very incommodious, and capable to receive but few Veſſels.</p>
               <p>Upon our approach to the Great Bay of <hi>Corinth,</hi> there were ſome Horſes ſtill to be ſeen, and the Fire was ſtill burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which the Baſſa had ſet to the Houſes. But the Enemy ſoon diſappearing, we underſtood by the Country People, who came to humble themſelves with the Primates of that place, that thoſe of <hi>Miſitra, Caritenae, Drapolizza,</hi> and other Towns, who had randezvouz'd to one particular Town, that they might march in an intire Body, ſtill ſtay'd at the Entrance into the <hi>Morea,</hi> and were under the Command of <hi>Mahomet</hi> Baſſa, who ſtay'd at <hi>Caritena,</hi> and had about Two thouſand Men; the reſt, to the number of Ten thouſand Families, being all the Inhabitants of the ſaid deſerted Places.</p>
               <p>There were found in the City many Pieces of Antiquity, among the reſt a Statue of <hi>Janus.</hi> We had alſo the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity in our Voyage, to ſee in the oppoſite part of <hi>Rumelia</hi> the Mountain of <hi>Parnaſſus,</hi> the Fountain of <hi>Helicon,</hi> ſo much celebrated by the Poets, not far from which there ſtands a Town which preſerves the Name ſtill: And not far from thence ſtands <hi>Pindarus,</hi> now all over Wooddy, the Grandeur of thoſe Ages being all devour'd by Time, and vaniſh'd.</p>
               <p>It was thought fit to ſend back the ſaid Veſſels to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of the <hi>Morea,</hi> and while they were conſidering what other Important Actions to go upon, they did not forbear to mind one thing of Principal Moment, which was to take a ſtrict view of the Streight, and of the Place itſelf, as well in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to neceſſary Deliberations, as to find out a way to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Return, if they ſhould attempt it, of the Turks
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107108:11"/>into the <hi>Morea;</hi> which as it could not be performed but with a ſtrong Force, therefore they ſet Sail with the whole Fleet to that Station, where they Imbark'd all their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Foot, marching the Cavalry by Land: They alſo fill'd ſome of the fourteen Galeots which they took in the Port of <hi>Lepanto</hi> with Italian Soldiers, to make uſe of in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the reſt. And with all that remain'd with the Cavalry, General <hi>Coningſmarck,</hi> when they came to the Place of Buſineſs, caus'd the Infantry to be landed, under the Command of a Serjeant Major of Batalia. Thus they poſſeſs'd themſelves of the City, where they lodg'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the beſt they could, and to the Fortreſs was diſpatch'd Colonel <hi>Bonomitti,</hi> with his own and Count <hi>Verroual</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; who preſently ſet up the glorious Standard of St. <hi>Mark.</hi> And there they found many Houſes untouch'd, with forty ſix Pieces of Cannon all Braſs, and four of Iron, beſides Ammunition and Victuals. Immediately His Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency diſpatch'd away three Galiots to the Caſtle <hi>Forneſe,</hi> with Letters to the Aga of that place, inviting him to a Surrender, but ſeverely threatning him if he refus'd, who immediate deliver'd up the Place to our Men, imbarking himſelf upon a Veſſel of <hi>Raguſa,</hi> by him freighted for <hi>Smyrna,</hi> leaving behind him an Hundred and fifty Turks, who being illuminated by Heaven, reſolv'd to be Baptiz'd and follow the True Faith. Upon the Caſtle they found nine Pieces of Braſs Cannon, and twenty of Iron.</p>
               <p>Now while it was believ'd that <hi>Mahomet</hi> Baſſa, with his Forces above-mentioned, was not as yet departed the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, there was ſome aſſurance that laying hold of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture while the Paſs was free, he had made the more haſte to get out of <hi>Rumelia,</hi> and retire to <hi>Thebes,</hi> where the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſquier had his abode, with thoſe Forces which he could retain in their Obedience. But then it was that all the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baneſes and Walachians in the Kingdom were in chaſe of the Ottomans that lagg'd behind, for the moſt part Women and Children; but the Value was Conſiderable, of Four thouſand of all Sexes and Ages, which they and the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers reſolv'd to make Slaves, finding them ſtraggling among the Mountains, whither, through the Violence of their Fears, they had made their Eſcapes. Nor were the Greeks exempt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107108:12"/>from the laſt Severities of the Turks, who, where-ever they paſs'd along, by force drave all into Slavery, and carry'd away all the Beaſts of Carriage, to carry their Baggage. Many Parties of the <hi>Albaneſi</hi> ventur'd as far as <hi>Megara,</hi> which is the firſt Main Land without the Iſthmus, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacking the Rear of the Fugitive Enemies, made many Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and gain'd a greater number of large and ſmall Beaſts which they brought off with them. Soon after the Deſires of General <hi>Coningſmark</hi> were accompliſhed by the arrival of the Ship St. <hi>Dominic</hi> at <hi>Zant,</hi> whither ſhe was ſent to fetch his Wife, and bring her to the Fleet, whither ſhe came, and with her a Convoy of ſeven Ships, under the Command of <hi>Zuanne Moroſini,</hi> on the Seventh of this Inſtant, with the Soldiers aboard, which were landed and joyn'd with the reſt, to ſupply the number of the Sick, which, as it was then reported, were many.</p>
               <p>By Letters from the Signior Captain of the Men of War, dated the Laſt of <hi>June,</hi> came Advice, that having ſhut up the Sultan Ships of the Turkiſh King, with ſeveral other Veſſels of the Barbarians, laden with Proviſions from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and Land-Soldiers, he kept them there penn'd up, having alſo met with certain Corſairs which he kept with him, as being bound from the Coaſt of <hi>Syria</hi> with Proviſions and Soldiers, and pretending to relieve the Beſieged.</p>
               <p>As to the diſpoſal of the Churches, made choice of in every one of the Places, conquer'd by the moſt Serene Republic, they are the faireſt of the Moſchees, of which there are a very great number.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Patraſſo,</hi> within the Fortreſs the <hi>Moſchee</hi> was given to the Franciſcan Fryers of the Order of the moſt holy Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Provincial <hi>Buonanome</hi> has the Poſſeſſion of it. And in the, City was given another with the Title of St. <hi>Andrews</hi> to the Barefoot Carmelite Fryers.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Lepanto</hi> the faireſt Moſchee was Conſecrated by the Name of St. <hi>James,</hi> and the Solemnity was performed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after the gaining of the City. In the Caſtle of the <hi>Morea</hi> another was dedicated to our Lady of Health or Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and a Prieſt was placed therein. In the Caſtle oſ <hi>Torneſe,</hi> another was dedicated to our Lady of <hi>Loretto;</hi> and St. <hi>Anthony</hi> of <hi>Padoua.</hi> But there was no Chaplain ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107108:12"/>nor any Diſpoſal then made at <hi>Corinth.</hi> The two Ships, the St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and the <hi>Factor of Zant,</hi> Maſter <hi>Anzolo Michiel,</hi> are return'd from <hi>Napoli</hi> in <hi>Romania,</hi> which in the time of the Sickneſs there, were ſent thither to rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force that Important City; but there being no need of any Reinforcement, they have return'd the Three hundred Foot which were aboard, tho' they have not prattic allow'd them as yet, becauſe thoſe parts are ſtill ſuſpected.</p>
               <p>The Captain Baſſa, with his Fleet, ſuffer'd heavily while his Fleet was infected with the ſame Diſtemper, ſo that he was forc'd to re-enter the <hi>Dardanels</hi> to recruit his Veſſels almoſt empty of Men. <hi>Scio</hi> and <hi>Senirna</hi> are infected with the ſame Diſtemper, but the Iſlands of <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Lemnos</hi> are free.</p>
               <p>The Metropolitan of <hi>Corinth,</hi> which is a Dignity of great Honor, came to viſit the Captain General, with a large Train of Prieſts of his own Religion; and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with the ſame Demonſtrations of Affection, as the Addreſſes of ſo worthy a Prelate were humble and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending, and becoming a Perſon ſo greatly eſteem'd both in theſe and other parts.</p>
               <p>And indeed, new Subjects come in every day to do Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to his Excellency; and to obtain poſitive Orders not to be moleſted by the Soldiers or Seamen, to the end they may undiſturb'd enjoy thoſe Felicities, which they have ſo long wiſh'd for in being freed from the ſlavery of the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Miſitra</hi> ſtill remains to reſemble the Ancient <hi>Sparta,</hi> rich in Gold and Merchandiſe, and peopl'd with Twelve thouſand Souls. His Excellency has ſent thither the Proveditor of <hi>Zar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata Palani,</hi> with Six thouſand <hi>Mainotts,</hi> and other Country Men, to compel it to ſubmiſſion by a Siege.</p>
               <p>The firſt fight of the Beſiegers brought the Affrighted Enemy to ſo much complacency, that they hung out a White Flag, and after Hoſtages given on both ſides, they went ſo far as to reſign three principal Members of this Place, to the Supreme Authority of his Excellency, with Letters from their Baſſa, that they were ready to abandon the whole Territory, provided they might have paſſage for themſelves,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107108:13"/>their Families, and their Baggage. But in regard they had held out to the laſt gaſpings of the whole Kingdom, and thereby had forfeited Compaſſion, he deny'd their Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions; only he was content, to let the Women, Children, and Aged Perſons to go; but as for them, they ſhould remain Slaves, with this Liberty to redeem themſelves at the price of Two hundred thouſand <hi>Reals;</hi> leaving them upon refuſal of both theſe Propoſals, to ſhut themſelves up within their Walls, from whence it would be afterwards his part to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel them by force of Arms.</p>
               <p>The three Commiſſioners being thus ſent back with the General's Anſwer, we are in expectation of the Reſolution of the Citizens.</p>
               <p>Upon the 13th. Inſtant, his Excellency went with a ſtout Body of Horſe and Foot, to viſit the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> or Neck of Land, between the <hi>Ionian</hi> and <hi>Egean</hi> Sea, and which joyns the <hi>Morea</hi> to the Continent, and march'd as far as the footſteps of the Ancient Walls, which cloſed up the ſame, made by the Grecian Emperor, in the year 1413. and demoliſh'd afterwards by <hi>Armurath</hi> the Second, in the year 1424. after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards re-edifi'd by the Captain General <hi>Luigi Loredano,</hi> who landed the Soldiers of his Fleet, under the Command of <hi>Bertaldo D' Eſte,</hi> by means of whoſe laborious Toil, as the Hiſtorians teſtifie, and the aſſiſtance of Eighty thouſand Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, in fifteen days they ſiniſh'd the whole Work, in the year 1463. fortifi'd with One hunderd thirty ſix Towers, and Three Motes, now diſmantled and levell'd, ſo that no footſteps thereof remain in many places. He alſo view'd the Fortreſs call'd <hi>Acro-Corinto,</hi> ſeated in a place of great advantage, which tho' it be plac'd upon a very high Hill, is nevertheleſs furniſh'd with Wells of excellent Water, as alſo the Fountain <hi>Pyrene,</hi> ſo much celebrated by <hi>Homer.</hi> The importance of the Place, and the eaſineſs of it to be made Tenable, induc'd him to believe that it was of neceſſity to be provided with all things neceſſary both for Defence and Offence, and requiſite Proviſions of Victuals; and <hi>Anzolo Michiel,</hi> a Gentleman of Diſcretion, Abilities and Vertue, was deſign'd extraordinary Proveditor for that place; being alſo reſolv'd not to let ſlip the remaining part of the Seaſon, without making ſome other progreſs in his Conqueſts, which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107108:13"/>will fall either upon <hi>Negroponte</hi> or <hi>Athens,</hi> yet not ſo, but that he will take his Meaſures from the Effects of the Seaſon, and the variety of the Weather, which he may meet with in the Seas of the <hi>Archipelago,</hi> and to facilitate his Voyage, the Foot and Horſe ſhall be left at <hi>Cortuno,</hi> which ſhall after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards be carry'd to the Coaſts of the <hi>Egean,</hi> from the other part of the <hi>Iſthmus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Signor <hi>Daniel Venier</hi> dy'd of an Inflammation, which kill'd him in few days; and <hi>Peter Marcello</hi> was conditional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly order'd to Command his Galley.</p>
               <p>The Knight, Sir <hi>Cittadella</hi> a <hi>Padouan,</hi> comes under Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, being ſent to be Governor of <hi>Corinth,</hi> which place will be well Garriſon'd.</p>
               <p>Many Families in <hi>Rumelia</hi> deſirous to paſs into the <hi>Morea,</hi> to withdraw themſelves from ſubjection to the Turks, have made their Applications by their Commiſſioners to the Captain General, and having had audience, ſeveral Barks, and ſome Gallies have heen order'd for their Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſportation.</p>
               <p>There is great ſollicitation made to remove with the Fleet, and make a long Voyage to the other ſtreight of the <hi>Egean,</hi> ſo to proceed upon other deſigns, which are agreed upon to advance the Fame of the Arms of the moſt Serene Republic.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:107108:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>From the Venetian Fleet, under</hi> Caſtle Novo <hi>in</hi> Dalmatia, September 16. 1687.</head>
               <p>THis moſt Serene Republic, makes it her Buſineſs to mind the Security and Proſperity of all Chriſtendom, and the Holy League, having generouſly reſolv'd to purge the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Sea of that peſtilent Rabble of <hi>Corſaires</hi> of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtel Novo,</hi> and other adjacent Places, which with their Barks and Pyracies they render impaſſible, and all the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Coaſts unſecure for Trade. To which purpoſe, at the vaſt expence of her own Treaſures, ſhe has rais'd a ſtrong Army in <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> under the Command of his Excellency <hi>Girolamo Cornaro:</hi> For that thoſe Places being attack'd and reduc'd, which ſerve as a Sanctuary and Security to thoſe Enemies of the Chriſtian Name, the Triumphant Standard of the Croſs will be gloriouſly advanc'd by the zealous Valour of the Venetian. Thereupon an Enterprize ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant being concluded upon, it was agreed that the Enemy ſhould be attack'd where-ever he ſhould be found. Nor was the Sieur <hi>Janco</hi> ſecond to any, a Perſon of great Courage, and much dreaded by the Turks; who ſetting out of <hi>Spalatro</hi> in company of his Morlacks, and underſtanding that in the Plains of <hi>Dunno,</hi> beyond <hi>Cettina,</hi> about Three hundred Turks were got together, went reſolutely to fight them; and the Fray being begun, having himſelf with his Cutlace laid a Turk ſprawling upon the ground, believ'd him dead: but the other having a Piſtol in his hand, let fly at the Victor and ſhot him. However, there were kill'd and taken fifty of the Turks by the <hi>Morlacks,</hi> with the loſs of only two Men; all their Tents and Baggage were alſo taken.</p>
               <p>His Excellency therefore being reſolv'd upon his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Deſign, took ſhipping with his whole Army, and after contrary Winds which kept our Fleet thirteen days
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107108:14"/>at Sea, not without ſome detriment to the Horſe for want of Water and Forrage, our Fleet arriv'd with a propitious Wind, the ſecond of <hi>September,</hi> within the Roſes over againſt <hi>Caſtle Novo,</hi> which to the number of a hundred and thirty, or more Sail, made ſuch a Majeſtic ſhew of it ſelf, which conſider'd together with the Courage of thoſe abroad, ſtrook no ordinary Terror into the Turks: Which was by them made the more manifeſt, for that they let us ſile off our Men within Cannon ſhot, without ſo much as firing one Gun at us.</p>
               <p>The next day about Six a Clock, our Army landed not above two Miles from the Fortreſs, and then advancing ſlowly in good Order toward the ſame Fortreſs, and about a Mile from the ſame, they found ſome Oppoſition from the Turks, who being got to the top of a little Hill, and poſted in a Church, call'd by the name of <hi>Santa Veneranda,</hi> occaſion'd a bloody Skirmiſh. Preſently the General diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd away Orders to the Auxiliaries, to advance with the Gallies within Cannon ſhot, and to bring their Guns to bear upon the Enemy, by that means to diſloge them, and to haſten their own landing, to reinforce our Men. At the ſame Inſtant, the General mounting a Horſeback with all the Cavalry, conſiſting of Four hundred able ſtout Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers commanded by the moſt Illuſtrious <hi>Giovanni Loredano,</hi> appointed by his Excellency Proveditor of the Cavalry in the Camp, and ordering the Oltramarine Militia to land, threw himſelf perſonally together with them, into the Place of the Conflict, which laſted for two hours with great obſtinacy on the Turks ſide. But at length the Auxilaries being landed under the protection of the continual firing of the great Guns from the Gallies; and our new Reinforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments being diſcern'd by the Turks, who ſurrounded his Excellency in very good Order, the Enemy retir'd toward the place continually skirmiſhing, and firing upon our Men; who having poſſeſs'd themſelves of the moſt advantageous Poſts of the ſaid Church, the Marqueſs of <hi>Borro,</hi> Serjeant Major of Battalia, went in the Night time to take a view of an advantageous Poſt, in a Houſe within Cannon ſhot of the lower City: where our <hi>Banditti</hi> of <hi>Abruzzo</hi> being poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and our paid Foot being entrench'd a little behind to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107108:15"/>with the Auxiliaries, his Excellency commanded two of our Gallies, commanded by <hi>Ludovic Balbi,</hi> and <hi>Benetto Zorzi Querini</hi> to take two ſmall Veſſels grappl'd together, and bring them within ſhot of the City, which was done not without great difficulty, by reaſon of the continual firing of the Enemy, tho to no purpoſe. The ſame day Eighty Men were kill'd of the Enemy, together with three Aga's, which was told us by a Slave that was taken Priſoner. And of ours five or ſix were ſlain, among whom a Knight of <hi>Malta,</hi> and ſome few common Soldiers, with two Knights of <hi>Malta</hi> wounded.</p>
               <p>The fourth day upon opening the Trenches to advance our Works, our Men found obſtinate reſiſtance from the Turks, who having ſtrengthen'd themſelves in another Houſe, and entrench'd themſelves within half Piſtol ſhot of our people, there happen'd all that day continual firing on both ſides, not without ſome loſs of blood, beſides, that the great Guns continually plaid upon our Battalians, and did us ſome miſchief. However, the Pinnaces fail'd not to play continually upon the low City with their Bombs, to the conſiderable damage of the Enemy.</p>
               <p>The Fifth day his Excellency obſerving the Reſolution of the Turks, who vigorouſly maintain'd their Poſt in the foreſaid Houſe, reſolv'd to bring two Sacres to diſlodge the Enemy from that Poſt. For the Execution of which deſign the Guns arriv'd about the 21ſt. hour, at what time they were mounted, and began their Battery upon the ſaid Houſe, which did not a little ſcare the Enemy; who having never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs ſecur'd themſelves with new Trenches, as alſo the advantage of a continual Rain and Wind on their ſide, thoſe advantages not only hinder'd the battering the Houſe, but very much endamag'd our Men, who while they endeavour to keep their Muskets dry, were themſelves almoſt drown'd in the Rain, which fell ſo exceſſive that Night, that it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to ſhrow'd their Arms.</p>
               <p>The Fifth day, tho' it continu'd rainy Weather, yet acts of Hoſtility did not ceaſe for all that, for their was conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual firing of Small-ſhot on both ſides, and continual ſhoot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as well from the upper Town, as the Caſtle with their Cannon, but ſo ineffectual to us, that we receiv'd little or
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107108:15"/>no damage, tho' the Turks were tormented by the Bombs of our ſmall Frigats, which the Sieur <hi>Pietro Duodo,</hi> having by Order of his Excellency brought within an eaſie reach of the Town, very much incommoded the Town by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual firing their Bombs, to the number of five hundred, among which there was one that brought to the ground a part of one of their Moſchees, and another fell into one of their great Towers over againſt the upper Caſtle, while they landed their Cannon and Mortar Pieces to perfect their Battery.</p>
               <p>Upon the 6th. day, the Turks made a ſhift to advance to our Battery of the two Sacres, which were valiantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by our Dragoons in the Poſt, advanc'd by the <hi>Brandi Stocchi</hi> of our Soldiers, upon which day the number was ſmall either of ſlain or wounded.</p>
               <p>The 8th. day, being the Feſtival of the Bleſſed Virgin, was deſign'd by his Excellency to land more Men upon the Weſt ſide, to the end there might be a Communication between our Men, and to prevent the like between thoſe that were beſieg'd in the upper Fortreſs and the lower. For the Execution of which, the Auxiliary Gallies were commanded by their continual firing to ſecure our landing, at what time our four Gallies, with the Militia aboard them, with ſeveral ſmall Veſſels grappl'd together, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd to the Weſt ſide, the Proveditor General leading the way with his Feluque. The firſt that landed were Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred Dragoons, who were plac'd in the Van, on purpoſe to take any advantageous Poſts, who found certain Houſes for ſhelter near the City, to the ſuccour of whom his Excellency ſent a good number of the paid Soldiers of the Galeots, as alſo a conſiderable number of the <hi>Morlacks</hi> of <hi>Spalato,</hi> and <hi>Chiſſa.</hi> At length the Turks ſecur'd from the frequent Peals, as well of our Auxiliary Gallies, as our own, his Excellency in perſon cauſing two Battalions of Infantry to land, the Turks retir'd, leaving the Houſes of the City expos'd to Plunder, which conſiſted of ſome ſmall quantity of powder'd Fleſh, the Truks having carry'd away all the reſt into the Fortreſs. At the ſame time the <hi>Malteſi</hi> and <hi>Papalines,</hi> who that day guarded the Poſt upon the Weſt ſide, where the Turks were fortifi'd in a certain Houſe,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107108:16"/>from whence they had not a little perplex'd our Men, having got over the Trenches with Drums beating, advanc'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Turks, who diſmay'd to ſee the Courage of the Aſſailants, baſely quitted their Poſts, which was poſſeſs'd by the <hi>Malteſi,</hi> who not ſo content, trarſported by their Courage, attempted to make their way into the City, in the hurly burly and confuſion of the Turks, that throng'd into it. Which fell out unfortunately, for that near the City, they met with a numerous Embuſcado, where five Horſemen were ſlain, whoſe Heads the Turks cut off, and took away their upper red Coats, with the white Croſs upon their Breaſts, and about twenty more were wounded, beſides a good number of their Foot kill'd, as ſome report ſixty, as others ſeventy.</p>
               <p>In the mean time our <hi>Peraſtines</hi> crept down from a little Hillock to the Cavalier of the Fortreſs, and advanc'd to another Poſt within Musket ſhot of the ſame Forts, in hopes to have cut the Embuſcado in pieces, which had ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damag'd our Auxiliaries, but the misfortunes of the Rain, which cauſed great overflowings of Water at that time, would not permit them to make any other attempts, while our Men had all their Fire Arms all over much wet. Only they made a ſhift to lodge themſelves within Musket ſhot of the City, the <hi>Peraſtines</hi> entrenching themſelves near the upper Caſtle, and the <hi>Malteſi</hi> retreating in good Order to the Poſt, firſt taken from the Turks.</p>
               <p>The 9th. day his Excellency deſign'd to go in perſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view the Poſt, poſſeſs'd by the <hi>Peraſtines,</hi> as alſo that which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the upper Caſtle, and riding a Horſeback to that part; the Turks who obſerv'd it, to ſhew their Courage, Sally'd out of the Caſtle, to the number of Four hundred, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to recover the Poſt which the <hi>Malteſi</hi> had gain'd the day before, and then defended by the Marqueſs of <hi>Boro,</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant Major of <hi>Battalia:</hi> But they were receiv'd by ours with hail of Musket ſhot, ſo that being beaten back, they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to win the Poſt which was kept by the <hi>Peraſtines.</hi> To which purpoſe with large, Poles in their hands, they advanc'd toward their Trenches: Upon their firſt Charge the <hi>Peraſtines</hi> were a little diſorder'd; but being encouraged by the preſence of his Excellency, who imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:107108:16"/>ſending a good Body of the ſaid Militia to their Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, they forc'd the Enemy to retreat. Our ſmall Frigates alſo purſu'd their firing into the City and the Lower Caſtle, with wonderful Effects. That day there was but little Rain, but the ſame night following it fell with an unſpeakable violence.</p>
               <p>The Tenth day, his Excellency caus'd two great Cannons of Fifty pound Bullets to be mounted, which, together with two more of Twenty pound, were to batter the Lower For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs, but the Rain was ſo violent that there was no playing of them: However, they were mounted, and upon the Eleventh, at Night, they play'd upon the lower Caſtle from the Weſt. By this means His Excellency thought to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a Parley; to which purpoſe he ſent the Sieur <hi>Doliza Dicattaro,</hi> well known to them, who approaching the City in a Feluque, he was anſwer'd in Musket-language, tho' without any hurt done to any that were in the Felnque.</p>
               <p>On the Eleventh, we began to play upon the Enemy with our Battery, and it was our good Fortune with two ſhot of a Cannon of Fifty pound Bullet to light into their Platform, to the conſiderable damage of the Enemy. The Enemy made good their Defence with extraordinary Courage, more eſpecially expecting to be reliev'd by the Baſſa of <hi>Azugouina,</hi> who was approaching to their ſuccour with Four thouſand Men; and at this Inſtant, we are preparing to march forth to meet him and give him Battel; to which purpoſe His Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency alſo goes in Perſon, and it is hop'd that our Courage will be ſuch as to beat the Enemy.</p>
               <p>Toward the Evening of the Eleventh Day, an Old Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was taken Priſoner, whom the Turks made uſe of to ſend to the Baſſa. There was found about her under one of her Breaſts, a Letter, wherein the Beſieged earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought the Baſſa's Relief.</p>
               <p>Upon the Twelfth, Letters were brought to His Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency from a Confident, which ſet forth the weak Condition of the Baſſa, who was not able to muſter together above Eight hundred Turks: Which is the more probable, becauſe it comes from a Perſon of Credit: and a Conſident of the Baſſa's. There are ſome that report him not above Four thouſand of all that he can ſcrape together. However,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107108:17"/>His Excellency is reſolv'd to meet him, tho' 'tis ſuppos'd the Baſſa will not advance forward. This day our Batteries have conſiderably endamag'd the the lower Caſtle; beginning to batter the upper parts to take from them their Places of Shelter, and chiefeſt Offence, which conſiſts in a great Piece of Cannon of Fifty pound Ball, and two Falconets, which play hard upon the Battery. The Turks have this day made many ſhot to diſmount our Battery, but with no ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. At this Inſtant His Excellency is gone to the advanc'd Poſt, to review our Batteries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>From the Venetian Fleet, under</hi> Caſtel Nuovo, <hi>in</hi> Dalmatia.</head>
               <p>THe Siege of <hi>Caſtel Nuovo</hi> continuing with extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary vigour on the part of the Venetians, as has been declar'd in the laſt. Upon the Twelfth day, the Turks ſhew'd but little Courage, ſo that ours got ground, and the <hi>Abruzzeſi</hi> extended their Line with an Intention to encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs the Upper Fortreſs. In the Night-time about Seventy Chriſtians, Men, Women and Children, that were in the Upper Fortreſs, render'd themſelves, who related that they were very much peſter'd by the Carkaſſes of the Turks, who lay ſlain in their way, to the number of a hundred, ſlain in the Skirmiſhes of the former days: That an hundred and thirty lay wounded in the Caſtle, and about forty ſick, that the wounded periſh'd for want of skilful Men to look after them: That the Beigh, or Principal Commander, was ſlain upon the Eight day by the <hi>Malteſi:</hi> That the Governor of the Upper Fortreſs lay very ill; and that if that day the Rain had not fallen ſo violently, but that our Men in the purſuit of the Enemy had enter'd the City, the Turks, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may'd with the Iſiue of the Conflict, would certainly have left the Gates open in the Conſternation of their flight; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that the Conduit being broken, they muſt of neceſſity
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107108:17"/>have been forc'd to a Surrender for want of Water, had not the Rain fallen.</p>
               <p>The ſame-Day, His Excellency ſent for a Mortar-piece from the Weſt ſide, in regard the Bombiſts ſent from <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> were buſied in raiſing of a New Battery.</p>
               <p>This Day appear'd two Deputies from the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>Raguſa;</hi> the one to Congratulate His Excellency for the News of the Conqueſt of <hi>Morea,</hi> the other was ſent to the General of <hi>Malta</hi> upon the ſame account.</p>
               <p>The Thirteenth we finiſhed our Weſt and Eaſt Lines, and joyn'd them together; as for the Turks, they ſhut themſelves up in the City, and there ſtood upon their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
               <p>The ſame Day two Turks were made Slaves, ſent from the Baſſa of <hi>Archigouina</hi> with Circulatory Letters to the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories and Villages adjoyning, with Orders to raiſe Forces within their Limits; but not a Man was rais'd, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that they had no Men fit for Service.</p>
               <p>After Dinner, came to the Camp ſome of the Principal of Mount <hi>Niſita,</hi> in the Sclavonian language, Mount <hi>Ninick;</hi> where lye ſeveral ſmall Territories confining upon Mount <hi>Negrini,</hi> of the Greek Church. They ſurrender'd themſelves wholly to the diſpoſal of the Serene Republic, with all their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, two days diſtant. They left Ten Hoſtages, and the Chief Heads were rewarded with a Donative of an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Checkines.</hi> They reported that a Turk that was woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the laſt Battel of <hi>Hungary,</hi> was by the Prime Viſier Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Baſſa of <hi>Archigouina,</hi> who rambles up and down pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up what Fugitives he can find, to ſuccour this Place; but the Subjects of <hi>Niſita</hi> were reſolv'd openly to declare for the Republic of <hi>Venice.</hi> To which purpoſe they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted a Standard; upon which one was given them, they promiſing within three or four days ſuch a ſufficient Number, as ſhould be able to hinder the Paſſage of the Enemy. For which His Excellency promis'd an Exhibition of a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Checkines,</hi> every time they ſhould rout the Enemy's Forces. In the Night, two Pieces, Fifty Pounders, were deſir'd for the Battery againſt the Roundels, in the midſt of the City.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:107108:18"/>
               <p>The Fourteenth, two Mortar-Pieces were brought from the Weſt, and a Cannon-ſhot fell into a <hi>Palander,</hi> and wounded two Men, and another fell into the General's <hi>Caick,</hi> while it was rowing a Mortar-Piece a-ſhore, and hurt two of the Rowers. The Turks toward the Sea ſent forth ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Women to fetch Water, which could not be prevented by our Men, by reaſon of the Aſſiſtance which the Enemy gave the Women. At the ſame time a Turk flew up in the Air, being toſs'd up by the breaking of a Bomb. The ſame day, Advice came, that the Baſſa's of <hi>Arcigouiana</hi> and <hi>Albania</hi> were within four hours March of our Army, with a conſiderable number of Turks and Chriſtians; ſo that we ſtood all the time to our Arms: The Paſſes were re-inforced with other Companies, and with an Hundred and Twenty <hi>Zupponi</hi> that came in the mean time under three Banners; and from thoſe Fortifications were flung about Six hundred Bombs.</p>
               <p>The Fifteenth, came Letters to His Excellency from <hi>Raguſa,</hi> that the Turks were at a ſmall diſtance off, and that the next Morning they would Attack the Trenches. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon His Excellellency review'd the Poſts; the Batteries were advanc'd to the City, and the half of the Roundels Defence was beat down by the Cannon, being almoſt laid level, notwithſtanding the Walls were two Cubits thick.</p>
               <p>At the ſame time two Men of War were brought from the Eaſt part to play upon the Enemy, if they attempted to paſs that way: And for the ſame reaſon the Auxilaries were brought and planted upon the Weſt ſide, where our Men had thrown up a Counter-Line. Beſides that, they cut down ſeveral little Groves, under the Protection of which they might be ſecurely aſſail'd by the Turks.</p>
               <p>Toward the Eighteenth hour, the Turks appear'd, who came to relieve the Place, ſo ſoon as they had forc'd their way through the ſtreight Paſſes which were guarded by our Men; who inſtead of making that reſiſtance which they ought to have done, abandon'd their Station at the firſt ſight of the Enemy, and retir'd to certain Valleys. The Turks at the ſame time made long ſtrides towards our Lines upon the Weſt, of which the Count of <hi>Mutia,</hi> Serjeant Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor of Battalia, being advis'd, preſently got his Companies in order.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:107108:18"/>
               <p>And as ſoon the Turks with great Fury and loud Cries inveſted our Trenches; which prov'd much to their Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, while the Squadron on the Town-ſide being terrify'd, without ſo much as diſcharging a Musket, began to fly amain. So did the Squadron of Colonel <hi>Perini,</hi> being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order'd by the flight of the firſt; ſo that the Enemy made themſelves Maſters of our Works, which they began to ruin. But the Count of <hi>Mutia</hi> preſently diſpatch'd Colonel <hi>Adel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> with a Squadron of Dragoons, and another of Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deers, and reſtor'd the Battel. In flew alſo Colonel <hi>Conti,</hi> with his Men, encourag'd by the Squadron of <hi>Carponeſe,</hi> which, without ſtaying for Command, broke in, to the great advantage of the Combat.</p>
               <p>The Turks thereupon, try'd with a haſty March, and no longer able to make reſiſtance, after a long Fight, turn'd their backs, and betook themſelves to flight. The purſuit was attended with a great ſlaughter, and they who had let them paſs by before, obſerving the Rout, fell upon their flanks; ſo that the <hi>Periniſts</hi> and <hi>Montenegrini</hi> much encreaſed the Havock.</p>
               <p>His Excellency rode to the Place of the Conflict, to animate his Men, and to be ready with Relief upon all occaſions; nor would he ſtir, till ſeveral Heads and Colours were brought him, with certain Advice of the Victory.</p>
               <p>There were above Three hundred Heads to be ſeen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many ſlain upon the Place; Twelve Colours, and Twelve Slaves, of which one was of <hi>Caſtle-Novo,</hi> who had got out of the Town to ſolicit the Relief; a Principal Perſon of <hi>Scutari,</hi> very Rich, and one <hi>Cozzo</hi> of <hi>Muſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Excellency ſhew'd the Signals of his Conqueſt to thoſe of the Upper Fortreſs, who might well obſerve the Fight, expoſing to their view the Heads that were cut off, the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and part of the Slaves, and gave the Beſieged to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that ſeeing they had no hope of Relief, there Army being routed; and conſidering the ſtreightneſs of their own Condition, they ought to ſubmit to the Victorious Arms of the Republick, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ceaſe all future fruitleſs Obſtinacy: But the Defendants cutting off all long Preambles, made Anſwer, It was not yet time, and at the ſame Inſtant di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcharg'd a Volley of Musket-ſhot.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:107108:19"/>
               <p>From the Slaves they underſtood, that the depos'd Baſſa of <hi>Archigouina</hi> was Elected Baſſa of <hi>Boſſina;</hi> that he who had exchang'd with him, had only Ten Perſons in his Train; that the Remainder, part Chriſtians, part Turks, amounted not to above Four thouſand at moſt; that they both came with a Body of Two thouſand ſeverally; and that the Baſſa of <hi>Aroigouina</hi> was the Perſon that inveſted our Men, the Baſſa of <hi>Boſſina</hi> ſtaying behind; and that the Government of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſa</hi> had accommodated theſe Commanders both with Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Money.</p>
               <p>But notwithſtanding Night came on, the Turks were pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu'd by the Militia, among whom the <hi>Sclavonians</hi> ſignaliz'd themſelves, who ſerv'd in the Galleys, the Burghers of <hi>Spala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro, Sebenico</hi> and <hi>Trau,</hi> who were the firſt that leap'd out of the Redoubts with their. Swords in their hands againſt the Enemy.</p>
               <p>Upon this Victory, which coſt little Chriſtian Blood, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended the Conqueſt of this Place. So that</p>
               <p>In the Evening, all the Guns in the Fleet were ſhot off in Token of Victory, and a Squadron of <hi>Morlacks</hi> was ſent to re-inforce the advanc'd Poſts.</p>
               <p>The Sixteenth, His Excellency caus'd <hi>Te Deum</hi> to be ſung, as a return of Thanks to Heaven; while the Enemy turning their backs, retreated a whole days March from theſe Parts. Eight Slaves were alſo brought in, of which one was the Brother of a Captain of a <hi>Dolcignota</hi> Galley, and a Colonel of <hi>Maſter;</hi> alſo two Heads, the one of the <hi>Giambeck</hi> of <hi>Boſſina,</hi> who Commanded a Thouſand Perſons; the other of a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of <hi>Retino.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Among the other Heads before-mentioned, that of the Brother of the Slave of <hi>Scutary</hi> came to be known. The ſame day, two of the Cannons which were in the Upper Battery, were remov'd into the Lower, and another Battery was built of two Pieces of Fifty; ſo that the Place was play'd upon with a Battery of Ten Pieces.</p>
               <p>Soon after, His Excellency expos'd the Heads and Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dards a ſecond time, and made a ſecond Summons; but was Anſwer'd, That ſo long as the Red Standards were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplay'd upon the Walls, it would be a Sign of Hoſtility;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:107108:19"/>That it was not a Time for Treaties, and that God would aſſiſt the Defendants.</p>
               <p>That day the Batteries beat down altogether the Defence of the Roundel, and they raiſed Bonnets and Lines to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>round the Fortreſs.</p>
               <p>A Bomb falling upon ſome pieces of Timber and Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials of Earth, reduc'd all to Aſhes. Our Militia alſo on the Eaſt-ſide, by the benefit of the Night, poſſeſs'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of a Houſe near to the Caſtle, being a fit place to form a Shelter for Miners. The <hi>Malteſi</hi> alſo having got ground, threw up a Line of Circumvallation to ſurround the Caſtle, and as they were making a great round Platform, the Turks ſally'd out to hinder them, but were beaten back.</p>
               <p>The Fifteenth, a Battery was finiſh'd of one great Gun of Fifty, and a Cannon of Twenty, and two Mortar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieces of Five hundred on the Eaſt-ſide, and began to play upon the Curtin of the City near the Roundel, which open'd a Breach in the ſolid Wall, but not low enough.</p>
               <p>About the middle of the day was brought a Colours, and the Head of one <hi>Deli,</hi> a Perſon of Quality, cut off by one of the Chief of the <hi>Peraſtines</hi> who guarded the advanc'd Poſts; and he that was the Meſſenger ſaid, that the Enemy was very much ſhatter'd in their flight; that many of our People were at their heels, cutting of thoſe that lagg'd behind and thought to hide themſelves. Another Slave ſaid, That the Enemy were above Four thouſand, moſt Men that were forc'd from Provinces afar off; and that the Baſſa of <hi>Boſſina,</hi> with Two hundred Horſe only, remain'd to ſhew his back to his own People. That he was over-rul'd to attack our Men by the Baſſa of <hi>Arcigouina,</hi> who was the firſt that with Two hundred Horſe enter'd our Trenches, and that in his flight the Baſſa of <hi>Boſſina</hi> was flightly wounded. No more then Eight hundred of our Men enter'd the Battel, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers'd ſo great a Party of the Turks, with the loſs of only Four of ours, and Five and twenty wounded.</p>
               <p>After Dinner, the Beſieged ſet up Gabions, and pali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zado'd the Baſtion and Roundel, and gave ſome diſturbance to thoſe that aſſiſted at the Battery. But our Men turning two Cannon upon them, the Shot fell among the Gabions,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107108:20"/>turn'd them topſie-turvy. and made a great ſlaughter of the Turks. After that, four Mantelets were ſet up in places agreed upon, which ſerv'd for Defence of the Miners, who wrought underneath. All night it Rain'd, and the Turks made a great Salley, in hopes to ſurprize our Men; and it might have fallen out luckily for them, for our Men began to fly in diſorder, and made loud Cries: But that, inſtead of encouraging the Enemy, rather daunted them; ſo that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving they ſhould meet with a numerous Oppoſition, they retreated without any more to do.</p>
               <p>The Eighteenth, the Enemy mounted two Falconets, the one upon the Great Tower toward the Sea, the other upon the Caſtle of the City; which very much prejudic'd the Camp. But one of our Bombs reveng'd us; for lighting upon a Barrel of Gun-Powder in the Upper Fortreſs, it did great damage, beſides the killing of twenty Perſons, Men and Women.</p>
               <p>The ſame day, we had Advice, that the Baſſa's before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd, upon a Muſter of their Men, found miſſing Six hundred thirty five, among which were between Fifteen and Twenty five Perſons of Note, for the moſt part Officers, whoſe heads were known by the Slaves. Moreover the Baſſa of <hi>Albania</hi> goes about picking up Soldiers as the other two did, not ſparing Perſons exempt, to encreaſe his Number, and try the Fortune of another Combat, reſolv'd to do their utmoſt to relieve the Place, which they believe to be reduc'd to the laſt Extremity.</p>
               <p>Late there came a Bombiſt, ſent by the moſt Serene Duke of <hi>Tuſcany;</hi> whereupon Orders were given to get ready new Mortar-pieces. At Night the Turks with a numerous Sally gave us an Alarum, but were valiantly repell'd.</p>
               <p>The Nineteenth, a Perſon of the Greek Church being ſtopp'd who had been abroad the night before, reported, That the Defendants, ſeeing the ill ſucceſs of the Fifteenth Day, believ'd it to be a Deſign concerted among our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, not being able to conceive that ſo great a Power ſhould be ſo eaſily routed; but being afterwards certify'd of the Truth of the Fact, they were very much diſheartned; yet they remain'd obſtinate in their own Defence, and had
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:107108:20"/>made a Circle of Palizadoes, Beams and Faggots round about the Breach.</p>
               <p>There were found three Turkiſh Colours more in the hands of the <hi>Peraſtines,</hi> and a Slave of Quality and Honor, <hi>Ali Bei.</hi> Of ours in the Campaigne between kill'd, wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſick, there are about ſix hundred. But the three hundred <hi>Florentines</hi> being arriv'd, and thoſe of <hi>Baraide</hi> being not far off, the loſſes of the Camp were ſufficiently ſupply'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>From the Venetian Camp, under</hi> Caſtle Novo <hi>in</hi> Dalmatia, September 19. 1687.</head>
               <p>THE Turks made more ſallies upon the City, ſhewing very great Courage.</p>
               <p>They kill'd ſeveral Soldiers, and among others wounded a Knight of <hi>Malta,</hi> who dy'd the next day.</p>
               <p>Our Men made themſelves Maſters of divers little Houſes adjoyning to the City, ſtill more and more uniting their Lines, ſtriving alſo to hinder the Communication between the upper Fortreſs and the City; which they continually plaid upon with their Batteries, and infeſted with their Bombs; no leſs diligent in haſtening their Mine, tho' that Night they could not do much, by reaſon of the abundance of Rain that fell.</p>
               <p>The 20th. the Florentine Forces arriv'd, Soldiers pick'd and call'd out of the Garriſons of <hi>Livorn,</hi> commanded by Signor <hi>Cancelli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i,</hi> to the number of Three hundred.</p>
               <p>There was alſo about the ſame time taken young Lads that belong'd to the City, who reported, that the Turks la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd continually to fortifie the Breach, and that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to caſt up two Pieces of Fortification, that ſhould with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all Aſſaults. Whereupon all the Artillery was brought to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:107108:21"/>bear upon that part to level the Breach, and beat down the Tower.</p>
               <p>That Night our Men near rais'd their Works, and cleans'd their Trenches, which the Rain had ruin'd.</p>
               <p n="21">21ſt. They made Ladders to ſtorm the City in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places, and weakned the Defence of the Beſieged.</p>
               <p>A report alſo ran that <hi>Soliman Sangiac</hi> of <hi>Scutari</hi> was get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Forces together, to relieve <hi>Caſtle Novo.</hi> Whereupon his Excellency deſign'd to ſend ſeveral Veſſels and Men of War, under the Command of Signor <hi>Duodo,</hi> toward <hi>Dnlcigna,</hi> a City greatly belov'd by the <hi>Sangiac,</hi> on purpoſe to divert him; but the Time would not permit him.</p>
               <p>Thereupon they proſecuted their Mining with more induſtry then before, to the end they might come at the Foundations of the City, thereby to enlarge the Breach to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the City.</p>
               <p>The 22d. was ſpent in expediting the Men of War, and other Veſſels toward <hi>Dulcigna,</hi> but the Rains, and contrary Weather would not ſuffer their departure.</p>
               <p>But then the Rumour increaſing of the Turks drawing together to relieve the City, they ſet themſelves to raiſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Works, and to finiſh ſome Bonnets.</p>
               <p>At which time there arriv'd other German Foot, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Command of Colonel <hi>Baracter,</hi> to the number of five hundred in all.</p>
               <p>The 23th. they went on finiſhing their Works, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Mines to perfection; not ceaſing to thunder from their Batteries, which were continually viſited by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, and his Lieutenant General.</p>
               <p>The 24th. the Men of War, and other Veſſels ſet ſail for <hi>Dulcigna;</hi> at which time the Turks open'd their Gate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Sea, which they always kept ſhut before, by which means they had Water to their own content.</p>
               <p>The 25th. a Mine was ſet to work under the upper Tower, to the end it might fall together with the City: But the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs was bad by reaſon of the Oppoſition of the Enemy, and the Engineer <hi>Baerbieri</hi> was wounded in the Head with a Stone; but the Mine toward the City advanc'd to the very ſides of the Wall.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:107108:21"/>
               <p>About the ſame time, the Enemy made a ſally unexpected<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Aſſailing our nearneſt Trenches, cut off the Heads of two of our Men, and carry'd away another.</p>
               <p>The 26th. the <hi>Peraſtines</hi> made themſelves Maſters to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the North, of the Turks Magazines, which they made uſe of inſtead of an Arſenal, ſeiz'd upon two Barks that were there, and a Mortar-peice.</p>
               <p>The ſame day they ſet the Mines to work at the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs, labouring more ſecurely under the protection of <hi>Mantclets;</hi> but to no effect, for that the Enemy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd the Workmen with Granado's, and continually throwing down Stones, the Ingineer <hi>Carnuto</hi> being wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed firſt in the hand with a Fuzee, and afterward in the Foot.</p>
               <p>While thus nothing of Military Diligence and labour was neglected, his Excellency reſolv'd to try what Policy would do, and conſidering there were great Diviſions in the Town, between the Inhabitants, and the Garriſon, conſiſting of many <hi>Albaneſe</hi>'s;</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Albaneſe</hi>'s therefore, the General deſign'd to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade to leave the Town, by the means of the <hi>Peraſtines,</hi> on purpoſe to weaken the Enemies Garriſons, and force them to a Surrender, when they ſhould find themſelves abandon'd by ſo conſiderable a part of their Defendants.</p>
               <p>Upon this, two of the Turkiſh <hi>Albaneſi</hi> were by the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtines</hi> towld forth, upon the General's Parol, that they ſhould receive no injury, who being treated with all civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, engag'd the reſt to depart the Garriſon the next Night, to the number of two hundred and twenty.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the mean time, all diligence was us'd to advance the Mine, but meeting with nothing but Free-ſtone, the work went on but ſlowly.</p>
               <p>The Turks, however, endeavoured to Countermine it, upon intelligence given them by the Fugitives, but meeting the ſame Oppoſition of Free-ſtone, all their induſtry was in vain.</p>
               <p>Now it was agreed with the <hi>Albaneſi,</hi> that they ſhould go forth at the great Tower, which looks toward the Sea; whereupon his Excellency imbarking three hundred ſelect Foot upon two Gallies, the <hi>Brazzana,</hi> and the <hi>Acheſana,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:107108:22"/>and himſelf going aboard a Feluque, he made it his deſign not only to get out the <hi>Albaneſi,</hi> but to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce his own three hundred Men into the Great Tower.</p>
               <p>But 'twas impoſſible for him to bring the <hi>Albaneſi</hi> to that. For tho' they were willing to leave the City themſelves, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence that they were deny'd their Pay, they could not be brought to forfeit their Allegiance to the Grand Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, by betraying the Place to his Enemies.</p>
               <p>Having therefore proceeded ſo luckily thus far, and the Breaches being ſufficiently widen'd, his Excellency reſolv'd upon a General Aſſault, ſeeing he could ſo ſuddenly bring his Mine to perfection.</p>
               <p>The 28th. it was agreed upon, that the Aſſault ſhould be delay'd, by reaſon of the ill weather, and the continual Rains that fell like a Deluge.</p>
               <p>The ſame day a Florentine Bombiſt let fly a Bomb into the Great Tower of <hi>Kernegh</hi> next the Sea Shore, which lighting upon ſeveral Barrels of Powder, ſent a great number of Turks into the Air with their Wives and Children.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Peraſtines</hi> having accompliſh'd their firſt deſign, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted ten more <hi>Albaneſi</hi> toward the Sea-ſide, who had let themſelves down from a great Tower, and after they had been made much of in the Camp, were put a board with the reſt.</p>
               <p>Soon after the Weather clearing up, the General in purſuance of his good luck reſolv'd upon a general On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet.</p>
               <p>And it was ſo order'd, that the Auxiliaries with the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, ſhould lie cloſe to the Shore, and play with their Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non for ſeveral hours together. Alſo the five Batteries plaid without interruption, Sieur <hi>Vicenzo Grittie,</hi> Provedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the Artillery, <hi>Signor di Bucant</hi> Superintendant, Signior <hi>Granceſco Maria Scotto,</hi> and Signor <hi>Franceſco Gonner Ville,</hi> behaving themſelves with extraordinary diligence, and aſſiſting with all their might at ſo important a Duty.</p>
               <p>Signor <hi>Giovan Battiſta Calbo,</hi> Signor <hi>Pietro Perini,</hi> Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendent, the <hi>Oltramarine</hi> Militia, the <hi>Peraſtines,</hi> and the reſt that belong'd to the Poſt on the North ſide, with
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:107108:22"/>Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Canagitti,</hi> were order'd to aſſail the City on that ſide.</p>
               <p>On the Breach ſide were order'd the <hi>Germans</hi> under <hi>Baraitex,</hi> the <hi>Florentines,</hi> and part of the Auxiliary Militia aſſiſted by divers Knights of the Order, and Companies of Dragoons.</p>
               <p>Thus the Granadiers being ſent before, the Soldiers ran up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Breach, enter'd the great Tower in part demoliſh'd; but the Houſes being deſtroy'd that were behind, was the reaſon that they could not thunder upon the Enemy, as they would have done with their ſmall Shot; yet many <hi>Florentines,</hi> Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Satonini,</hi> and others made their way to the Moſchee. But the Turks being fortified in the Houſes, kill'd <hi>Santonini,</hi> the Captain of the Granadiers, and a great many Souldiers of his Excellenties Guard, the Harquebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiers, and many other Florentines, the main Body of the Turks, with their Wives and Children, being got into the Caſtle of the City, from whence they ſhot without ceaſing.</p>
               <p>The Chriſtians having thus loſt the beſt of their Officers upon the Breach, with two Knights of <hi>Malta,</hi> and one wounded, it could not be gueſs'd, whither it were out of fear of ſome ſuppos'd Mine, or whither it were by the fall of a Banner ſet up by the <hi>Malteſi,</hi> not only <hi>Baraiter</hi>'s Companies, but the Gentlemen Auxiliaries began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat.</p>
               <p>However, this diſorder did not put the more Courage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous into any Confuſion, but having got the great Tower, with two Pieces of Cannon, and three Patarrs, they kept Poſſeſſion: the <hi>Abruzzeſi</hi> having bravely behav'd themſelves, in maintaining the Combat, being aſſiſted by the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Signor <hi>Bori,</hi> Serjeant Major of Battalia.</p>
               <p>Signor <hi>Giovanni Loredano,</hi> Signor <hi>Tranquillo Bolani,</hi> the Marqueſs <hi>Orologio,</hi> ſhew'd very great Courage: and all the while his Excellency attended by many Noble Volunteers, and other Adventurers, in all the heat of the Combat took no reſt, expoſing himſelf to all danger, and running from Hill to Hill to give out all fitting Orders, and to animate the Aſſailants, both with his Preſence, and his Exhortation.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:107108:23"/>
               <p>Signor <hi>Gramani,</hi> the Lieutenant General led up to the very brink of the Breach, encourag'd the Men in falling on, and forc'd back the Fugitives.</p>
               <p>Alſo Signor <hi>Lexio Balbi,</hi> Governor of <hi>Cattaro,</hi> and <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardo Barbaro,</hi> being near to the <hi>Prazza</hi> and the Breach, were punctual at this time of Exigence.</p>
               <p>The 29th of <hi>September,</hi> a Turk of <hi>Tabiach</hi> was taken, who having been in <hi>Caſtle Novo,</hi> was making his eſcape to his own Country, and reported that there were burnt in the great Tower the day before, by the Barrels of Powder fir'd by the Bomb many Goods of Value, and about One hundred and ſixty Perſons, Men, Women and Children.</p>
               <p>By and by his Excellency diſcovering the earneſt deſire of the <hi>Morlacks,</hi> and the Levies of the Territories of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benico, Trau, Spalatro</hi> and <hi>Cliſſa,</hi> as alſo thoſe of <hi>Cattaro,</hi> and the <hi>Montenegrine</hi> had to enter the Breach, he gave them their Liberty, to which purpoſe he caus'd the five Batteries to fire, and play upon the Caſtle, and the great Tower to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Sea, and the City Houſes for a good while, and then let them go on.</p>
               <p>They would have enter'd by the great Tower, but that being already won, and maintain'd by the paid Militia, it would not be permitted them, ſo that they were neceſſitated to paſs on the other ſide the Breach, where they met with many difficulties in getting down, and were a good while before they could get footing. However, their Courage overcame the difficulty, and they got with three Colours flying into the City; about forty recovering a Houſe, which they got poſſeſſion of. The reſt returning back with their Booty, making the others believe, that they retreated with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Walls, as being purſu'd by the Turks, were ſomewhat diſorder'd at the ſight, tho' without having damage, only <hi>Zuranne Marowich,</hi> Governor of the Men of <hi>Trau,</hi> being wounded in the City, with ſome few of the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; whom nevertheleſs, the Sieurs <hi>Balbi, Barbaro</hi> and <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolamo Bochio, Antonio Bochi,</hi> and Count <hi>Franciſco</hi> ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recover'd to their former Courage.</p>
               <p>Theſe things thus done, the General reſolv'd to ſend for ſome Petars to break open the Doors of the Houſes, where the Enemy had fortifi'd themſelves; and to fill up
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:107108:23"/>the Mores and Trenches with Timber and Bavins, and to Level, to make the Acceſs to the City more eaſie to the Body of the Army, and to fill the town with Soldiers, to which purpoſe there was brought together in a ſhort time a vaſt quantity of Tools and Materials. Toward Evening the Work going buſily forward, his Excellency, perſwaded ſome of the Turks, who were in the great Tower toward the Sea, to ſurrender, upon Condition that they ſhould be ſent away to the reſt of the <hi>Albaneſes,</hi> and ſo to have the Liberty to repair home to their ſeveral abodes. Who having thus quitted the great Tower in the Night, our Men took poſſeſſion of it, and found therein two Pieces of Cannon, one <hi>Saker,</hi> and a Standard: All this while our Men made diligent haſt with their Timber and Fagots to finiſh their Works, that they might be able to paſs from the Tower of the <hi>Abruzzeſi,</hi> to the Walls, and ſo get into the City; wherein the Signors <hi>Antonio Canel, Alviſe de Mula,</hi> and Count <hi>Porro,</hi> Colonel Conductor of the Soldiers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc'd ſignaliz'd their induſtry, together with Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Colonel <hi>De Termes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 30th being the day dedicated to the glorious St. <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolamo,</hi> Native and Protector of <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> it being the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God to reſtore to the Boſom of Chriſtianity, a place which formerly, through the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power, under the Magnificent Empire of <hi>Solyman,</hi> was eſteem'd the Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part of <hi>Turky</hi> againſt the Valor of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth; ſo it happen'd, that his Excellency being ſent with a noble Fleet, and a courageous Army quite reduc'd it, and ſubdu'd it, to augment the glorious Conqueſts of the moſt Serene Republic of <hi>Venice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Men being thus got into the City, made ſome Slaves, and ſet at Liberty ſeveral Chriſtians, that had been ſhut up by force within the Walls of the City. By the Priſoners we were inform'd of the death of <hi>Kirbaſſe,</hi> in the Oppoſition which was made to our firſt entring the Breach: which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the hearts and ſpirits of the reſt, they conſulted all that Night, what to do, finding it was but meer raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to think of holding out any longer. Thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they gave Commiſſion to a Turk to go and fall
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:107108:24"/>at his Excellency's feet, and implore Acts of Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>His Excellency therefore conſidering, that the Caſtle was fortifi'd, and which was more, fortifi'd by Nature withal, as being ſeated upon a high Rock, which it would require a long time to level, the following Articles were agreed upon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Turks with their Families ſhould depart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That they ſhould have Veſſels allow'd to tranſport them into</hi> Albania.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That they ſhould take nothing along with them, but ſuch effects as every one ſhould carry off arm'd with Sword and Piſtol.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Caſtle with all the Cannon, Standards, Arms, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition ſhould be deliver'd immediately to his Serene Highneſs the Duke of</hi> Venice, <hi>without any imbezelment, leaving the Rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gado's to his Excellencies Diſcretion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sending therefore for ſome <hi>Peraſtine</hi> Shallops, near to <hi>Caſtle Novo</hi> and drawing up the Soldiers on both ſides the way from the Caſtle to the Sea-ſide, in the preſence of his Excellency with all the Noble Men of <hi>Venice,</hi> and ſome Knights of <hi>Malta,</hi> to prevent the Soldiers and <hi>Morlocks</hi> from doing any injury to the Turks, they departed with all their Families, the Articles being punctually perform'd without any detriment to any perſon.</p>
               <p>The number of the Enemies, which were in the ſaid Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, amounted to near four hundred, what with Old Men, Wounded, and thoſe that were able to bear Arms, a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fierce and warlike, beſides about a thouſand Women and Children.</p>
               <p>The Firſt of <hi>October,</hi> the Turks which were in the upper Fortreſs, mov'd with the Indulgent uſage ſhew'd their Friends, made an Agreement upon the ſame Conditions, and had their departure ſo, and with the ſame Formalities; to the number of about a thouſand five hundred Men, Women and Children.</p>
               <p>Thus therefore fell to the Patrimony of the Moſt Serene
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:107108:24"/>Republic, one of the ſtrongeſt Holds of theſe Provinces, by the Valour of His Excellency <hi>Cornaro,</hi> after it had been ſome hundreds of years in Poſſeſſion of the Turks; being now made the Metropolis of <hi>Arcegouina,</hi> of which Signior <hi>Giro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamo Donato</hi> is appointed Governor, who having been Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of the City and Iſland <hi>Lieſſia,</hi> has, in the Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Commiſſary of the Camp, augmented the Honor of his Name, by his Sedulity in providing Proviſion for the Camp.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>From the Venetian Fleet, near</hi> Athens, Septemb. 21. 1687.</head>
               <p>HAving fetch'd their Compaſs round about the <hi>Morea,</hi> after the ſurrender of <hi>Miſitra</hi> at Diſcretion, and the Ruin of all <hi>Malvaſia</hi> with Bombs, to let thoſe haughty Turks underſtand the Power of the Serene Republic, His Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, the Lord Admiral, having rendezvouz'd his Fleet within the Streight of <hi>Corinth,</hi> in the Gulph of <hi>Egena,</hi> had an earneſt deſire to put an end to this years Campaigne with the Conqueſt of the <hi>Negropont,</hi> ſo much by him deſir'd; but conſidering, together with the other Superior Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Sea-Captains, who are admitted to Council, not only the difficulties of the Seaſon, far advanc'd in the Year, but the numerous Garriſon, of above Five thouſand Foot, which guarded that Precinct, and the Oppoſition which the Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquier might make, with the unanimous conſent of the whole Council, the Siege of <hi>Athens</hi> was agreed upon, to make way the next Seaſon for the Conqueſt of the <hi>Negro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pont.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thereupon the Men of War being ſent away to this Iſland in a diſtinct Squadron, to amuſe the Enemy, and draw the Seraſquier thither with his Forces, they ſteer'd directly toward Port <hi>Draco</hi> the Twentieth in the Evening, and the next Morning reach'd the Port.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:107108:25"/>
               <p>On the Twenty firſt they landed all their Militia, Horſe and Foot, but not ſo much as one Turk appear'd in the Field; whereupon they paſs'd on to <hi>Athens,</hi> and made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Maſters of the Town, which is only inhabited by the <hi>Greeks,</hi> while the <hi>Ottomans</hi> were retir'd into the Upper Encloſure.</p>
               <p>His Excellency underſtanding the ſtrong Situation of the Place, becauſe he would not be conſtrain'd to ruin it with his Bombs, ſummon'd the Defendants to a ſurrender: But the Enemy return'd Anſwer by word of mouth, That they were reſolv'd to hold out.</p>
               <p>The Twenty ſecond, two Mortar-pieces of Five hundred, and two Pieces of Cannon of Fifty, with two leſſer Guns of Twenty, were landed, which were eaſily brought to the Batteries that were raiſing, becauſe the Way was ſmooth and level, and but ſix Miles in length.</p>
               <p>On the Twenty third, they went on with their Work in raiſing their Batteries, during which labour, Serjeant Major <hi>Perez</hi> of the Regiment of <hi>Cleuters,</hi> dy'd the Twenty fourth at Night, of a wound receiv'd by a Musket-Bullet.</p>
               <p>The Twenty third, four more great Guns, two of Fifty, and two of Twenty, with two Mortar-pieces, were landed and brought to the Battery.</p>
               <p>The Twenty ſixth, they began to play with their Bombs upon the Fortreſs; one of which fell among their Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and fir'd a great part of it, to the great terror of the Beſieged, whoſe Defences began to fail them, their Parapets being ruin'd, and their great Guns diſmounted.</p>
               <p>The twenty ſeventh, This day the Trenches were open'd in order to make the Approaches, and to advance under the Walls.</p>
               <p>The Twenty eighth, towards Evening, through the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual playing of our Bombs, which fell all into the ſmall Encloſure, there hapen'd another great Fire, which encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon the fuel of the Houſes, and the continual playing our Bombs, endur'd ſo furious all that Day and the next Night, that the Enemy, aſtoniſh'd to ſee their Houſes and their Goods conſum'd, and their Families burn'd, reſolv'd to hang out a white Flag; and with earneſt and loud cries toward the Battery of the Super-intendant, Count <hi>Felice,</hi> begg'd 'em to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:107108:25"/>fling no more Bombs; which the Count underſtanding, caus'd all Hoſtility to ceaſe. Whereupon General <hi>Coningſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> gave leave for five Hoſtages to come forth, who being ſent to the Lord Admiral and Captain General, the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Capitulations were agreed upon: Which being tranſlated into the Turkiſh Idiom, one Copy was Sign'd by the Hoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges afore-mentioned, and the other ſent to the Fortreſs for punctual performance.</p>
               <p>His Excellency was glad of this Advantage; for tho' the Encloſure were but ſmall, yet it would have coſt a great deal of Time, and loſs of much Blood, to have Maſter'd it, by reaſon of the ſtrength of the Situation.</p>
               <p>Moreover it was of great conſequence, becauſe it Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands not only a Country of Spacious Extent, but alſo a Large and Wealthy City lying under it; a Place of great Trade for ſeveral ſorts of Merchandize that are brought to this Town; and which will therefore, in Time of Peace, bring great Revenue to the Public Treaſury.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Porto Lion, <hi>Septemb.</hi> 29. 1687.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALi Aga, Kuſſein Effendi, Kuſſein Aga, Kazi-Mahomet, Acamet Effendi Poſcha,</hi> Turks, ſent by the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Athens,</hi> in the Quality of Hoſtages, being all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Admiral Galley, to treat upon Conditions of Surrender with His Excellency Procurator, and Captain General. The Articles were agreed upon in the Form fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>That as an Act of Gracious Clemency, all the Turks, with their Wives and Children, ſhould be permitted to depart and quit the Encloſure within the ſpace of Five Days, begun this preſent Day; with liberty to carry forth as many uſeful Neceſſaries as every one can be able to carry on his back, Arms only excepted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>That they ſhall have leave at</hi> Noleggio <hi>to hire Veſſels at their own Charges, to carry them to</hi> Smyrna, <hi>or where they pleaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:107108:26"/>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>That at their departure they ſhall not put any force upon any Perſon that is not willing to go along with them, and ſhall leave all the Slaves behind them of what condition ſoever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>That in caſe there ſhall be at preſent found any want of Water, or any ſcarcity of Ammunition or Proviſions, that then theſe Articles are to be void and of no effect, and that the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants ſhall run the riſco of being compell'd to ſurrender at Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fourth of <hi>October,</hi> the Turks quitted the Place, to the number of Three thouſand Souls, of which there were about Five hundred Soldiers, and coming to the Sea-ſide with what Goods they could carry, were put a-board four Foreign Veſſels which they hir'd themſelves.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Ditto.</hi> Were found in the Caſtle eighteen great Guns of ſeveral ſorts; and tho' now it be a heap of Ruins, yet in a ſhort time it may be made a Place of great Strength.</p>
               <p>And in regard this Important and Glorious Conqueſt preſages not only to the Moſt Serene Republic, but to all Chriſtendom far greater Progreſſes, the City of <hi>Athens</hi> being now become Tributary ever ſince the beginning of this Month to the <hi>Venetian</hi> Armies; it will not be amiſs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Importance of the Situation, and the preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of that Ancient and moſt Renowned City.</p>
               <p>It is ſituated not far from the Sea-Coaſts, in the midſt of the Gulph of <hi>Engia,</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> and the Capital City of all <hi>Attica.</hi> It is now call'd by the Greeks <hi>Setine.</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Anciently <hi>Oenopria,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Egina,</hi> the Mother of <hi>Eacus</hi> and <hi>Rhadamanthus</hi> by <hi>Jupiter.</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peopled by Peſtilence; afterwards Re-peopled at the Prayer of <hi>Eacus</hi> by Emmets transform'd into Men, and therefore call'd <hi>Myrmidones.</hi>
                  </note> Anciently it had ſeveral Names from the ſeveral Princes that Reign'd therein, ſubject more then other to Changes of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It has a Cittadel built upon a Rock of Free-ſtone, ſurrounded with Walls joyn'd together to the Points and Circuit of the Rock, which is about a Thouſand and two hundred Paces in compaſs. Below the Hill are to be ſeen diſtinctly the Foundations of another Wall which ſurrounded almoſt all the whole City, and render'd it very difficult of acceſs. There, that is in the Cittadel, the Turks inhabit only, who are upon continual Guard againſt the Surprizes of the corſairs.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:107108:26"/>
               <p>In this Encloſure ſtood a Temple Dedicated <hi>To the unknown God:</hi> The Inſcription of whoſe Altar is ſtill to be ſeen; and tho' the workmanſhip be very coſtly for the Marble, yet it ſerves for no uſe, either to the Chriſtians or Turks.</p>
               <p>The Second part of this City, which is in the middle of the Firſt and Third, is inhabited ſolely by the Chriſtians: And the Third, which is lower than the two former, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains a moſt ſtately Palace of Marble; upon the Gate of which are Ingraven in Greek Characters, certain Words that ſignifie,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behold</hi> Athens! <hi>formerly the Seat of</hi> Theſeus.</p>
               <p>There is alſo to be ſeen in <hi>Athens</hi> another Structure, the moſt Beautiful that can be imagin'd, called the <hi>Pantheon;</hi> upon the outſide of which are engraved the Atchievments of the Greeks.</p>
               <p>Among other Miracles of this Sumptuous Building, at the larger Gate are to be ſeen two Horſes cut to the Life; the Workmanſtip of <hi>Prapiteles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Areopago,</hi> ſo much frequented in former Ages, is now reduced to a Monaſtic Solitude. Nor is there any thing of the Famous <hi>Academy</hi> remaining, but only a Greek Iuſcription which wiſhes Travellers a good Journey.</p>
               <p>It is thought that the Encloſure of <hi>Athens</hi> far exceeds that of <hi>Prague,</hi> the Capital City of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are an Infinite number of other Antiquities to be ſeen; among which the Arſenal of <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> after the <hi>Doric</hi> Order, where their Arms were ſtored; the Lanthorn of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes;</hi> the Tower of the Winds, of an Octaginal Figure, of which <hi>Andronicus Cireſtes</hi> gave the Model; and the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Theſeus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Formerly Learning and Learned Men flouriſhed in high re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in this City: Nevertheleſs She ſuffered her Viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, when in the 39th. <hi>Olympian, Draco</hi> inſtituted thoſe Bloody and Cruel Laws, which were afterwards abrogated and aboliſhed by <hi>Solon,</hi> the Fourth wiſe man of <hi>Greece,</hi> all but thoſe againſt Robbers. He puniſhed Lazineſs with equal puniſhment to death. <hi>Xerxes</hi> Four Hundred and Fifty Years before the coming of CHRIST having broke through the Streights of Mount <hi>Olta,</hi> now called <hi>Bocca di Lupo,</hi> or the <hi>Wolf's Mouth,</hi> burnt this City, tho' empty of Inhabitants, who at the ſame time were aboard Two Hundred Veſſels at Sea.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:107108:27"/>
               <p>From the Reparation of the Walls of this City, the Civil Wars had their Original; which after <hi>Greece</hi> was free'd from their Fears by the means of <hi>Leonidas</hi> and <hi>Spartan,</hi> divided all <hi>Greece</hi> into two Parties; while the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> pretended That there ought to be no place without the <hi>Peloponneſus,</hi> or <hi>Morea,</hi> where the Barbarous Nations might harbour and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify themſelves.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, In the Year Four Hundred and Four (before the birth of CHRIST) after a Fierce and Bloody War of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Twenty Years ſtanding, the Athenians being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown near to <hi>Aegos Potamos,</hi> they became ſubject to the Spartans.</p>
               <p>The Schools of <hi>Athens</hi> were the moſt Famous in the World; and while the City flouriſhed, bred the moſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Perſons, beyond the Schools of any other City or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>To <hi>Plato</hi> Succeeded <hi>Speusſippus;</hi> to him <hi>Zenocrates;</hi> to him <hi>Zenephon,</hi> ſo Famous in War: Then came <hi>Polemo, Crates, Crantor, Archeſilaus,</hi> who erected the <hi>Academy;</hi> whoſe Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was in the midſt between the Ariſtotelics and Platonics. <hi>Epicurus, Zeno</hi> the Founder of the Stoics; <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> the <hi>Tully</hi> of <hi>Greece. Ariſtotle</hi> founded the Sect of the Peripatetics, and his Succeſſors were <hi>Theophraſtus, Strato, Lycus, Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus, Lacides</hi> the Cyrenaean, and <hi>Diogenes,</hi> who raiſed the Fame of the <hi>Stoics</hi> to their higheſt Splendor.</p>
               <p>The Dukedom of <hi>Athens</hi> formerly reckon'd under their Juriſdiction One Hundred Seventy Four Villages or Towns; ſome of which were equal to many Cities. Now the greateſt number lies in the Plain of <hi>Meſogia,</hi> which are not a few.</p>
               <p>The Air is ſharp and clear, and conſequently very whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom; the Land is watered with moſt limpid Fountains, ſo that the Meadows produce all manner of Herbs, as well for Phyſic as for Sallads, which grew there as in a moſt Fruitful Garden: It abounds with Groves of Olive Trees, that yield a moſt perfect Oyl in great quantity, and ſerve for the uſe of the <hi>Grand Signior</hi>'s Palace at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of all her Mountains the chiefeſt is called <hi>Hymettus,</hi> which being mighty pleaſant and rich in Flowers, produces a moſt delicious ſort of Honey in great quantity, and excells all the Mountains of <hi>Greece,</hi> and perhaps of any other Country.</p>
               <p>In the ſeries of ſeveral Ages, it has been under the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:107108:27"/>of ſeveral Princes. <hi>Sylla,</hi> after a long Siege made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Maſter of it, and reduced it under the power of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bajazet</hi> triumph'd over it, when it was in ſubjection to <hi>Ariſtonicus</hi> the <hi>Epicurean</hi> Philoſopher. After that, <hi>Renizer Acciajali</hi> was Lord of it, from whom the Venetians won it; but afterwards recovered by the ſame <hi>Acciajoli,</hi> who poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed at the ſame time <hi>Attica</hi> and <hi>Boeotia.</hi> In the Year One Thouſand Four Hundred Fifty five, <hi>Dlahome</hi> II. beſieged it, and ſack'd it for want of Relief: Since which time 'till now, it remained all along in the Power of the Ottoman Emperors.</p>
               <p>The News of the great Victory was brought upon the the Tenth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> by a Feluque, which before ſhe came within ken, they knew not what the ſight might mean; but when they ſaw the Ottoman Colours and Standards ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to view, the People crouded to the Sea-ſide with ſhouts of Victory, and immediately the News ſpreading with the ſwiftneſs of the Wind, preſently a humming noiſe of Joy ran through all the Streets, while the People gathered in cluſters gave ear to the Speaker, who undertook to give a relation of the Victory, before he knew it himſelf. By and by the loud Acclamations of <hi>Long live St.</hi> Mark, filled all the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Skie, while the Bells with their brazen Throats pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd the joyful tidings to places more remote; and the Veſſels in, Harbour diſcharging their great Guns, with their gladſom terror diffus'd a pleaſing Satisfaction into the hearts of the Faithful.</p>
               <p>The ſame night the Moſt Serene Republick ordered Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires to be made upon the <hi>Piazza,</hi> accompany'd with ſeveral Volleys and Peals of ſmall and great Shot for two Evenings together; at both which times was to be ſeen the Great Steeple, reſembling the Caſtle of <hi>Babylon,</hi> with her Head and Shoulders ſtuck with Lights, reſembling an Immenſe Atlas, bearing upon his bunchy Back another Heaven, adorned with Stars propitious to the deſires of the People.</p>
               <p>In the Ducal Church was Sung <hi>Te Deum,</hi> accompany'd with Muſic ſo charming, that it was a difficult thing to judge, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Paradiſe did not congratulate us for the advantages of ſo great a Victory.</p>
               <p>And to ſhew that this Serene Republic never ſuffers Great Actions to go unrewarded, nor Valour to be deprived of its
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:107108:28"/>due Recompence. No ſooner did the welcom News of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Noble Atchievments reach the Ears of our Senators, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Names of the Commanders and Volunteers, who had been ſharers in an Action ſo renowned, but they vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Statue to be erected to the Admiral General <hi>Franciſco Moroſini,</hi> in the Council Chamber of <hi>Ten,</hi> with an Inſcription in Letters of Gold.</p>
               <p>To General <hi>Coningſmark,</hi> they ordered his Imployment to be continued for Five Years longer, with a conſiderable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to his Penſion, which is at this time above Twenty Four Thouſand Ducats a Year.</p>
               <p>To the Prince of <hi>Brumſwick</hi> was ſent a fair, large and rich Diamond, of a conſiderable value. A Sword enchaſed with Diamonds was ſent to the Prince of <hi>Turena.</hi> And acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment was made to the Marquiſs of <hi>Corbous,</hi> by augment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his annual Penſion, and declaring him Serjeant Major of <hi>Battalia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Medals of Gold were alſo ordered to ſeveral Officers, who ſignaliz'd their Valour in ſo important and famous an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize.</p>
               <p>And for a Concluſion, give me leave to inſert a ſhort <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyric</hi> Preſented to General <hi>Coningſmark,</hi> by Signior <hi>Antonio Martinelli;</hi> thus in Engliſh;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the Moſt Illuſtrious, and Moſt Excellent Lord, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> Coningſmark: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Rout of the Seraſquier, and the Conqueſt of</hi> Patraſſo, <hi>and the</hi> Dardanel <hi>of the</hi> MOREA.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>BRave Hero, with</hi> Venetian <hi>Lawrels Crown'd!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How loud thy Glories through the World reſound?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou but unſheath'ſt thy Conquering Sword, and streight</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Proſtrate</hi> Turk <hi>falls tamely at thy Feet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This the</hi> Seraſquier <hi>witneſs'd, bold in Fight,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Till in thy Looks he ſaw thy Courage writ:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But then thy Fame Deſpairing to with-ſtand,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quitted the Field to thy</hi> Supreme Command.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nor does</hi> Morea <hi>won, thy</hi> Name <hi>confine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So faſt th'affrighted</hi> Turks <hi>their Poſts reſign;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Too narrow is th'</hi> Achaian <hi>Theatre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Till at</hi> Byſantiums <hi>Walls thy Strength appear:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And that, if my</hi> Prophetic Muſe <hi>foreſee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Is the next</hi> Work by Heaven <hi>Ordain'd for</hi> Thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
